<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>P. Camus | Santander Meteorology Group</title><link>https://santandermetgroup.github.io/website-demo/author/p.-camus/</link><atom:link href="https://santandermetgroup.github.io/website-demo/author/p.-camus/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><description>P. Camus</description><generator>Wowchemy (https://wowchemy.com)</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Sat, 01 Jan 2011 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><image><url>https://santandermetgroup.github.io/website-demo/media/icon_hu58a305e0ce1458c8ebaf599b64640cde_12944_512x512_fill_lanczos_center_3.png</url><title>P. Camus</title><link>https://santandermetgroup.github.io/website-demo/author/p.-camus/</link></image><item><title>A methodology to evaluate regional-scale offshore wind energy resources.</title><link>https://santandermetgroup.github.io/website-demo/event/2011-a-methodology-to-evaluate-regional-scale/</link><pubDate>Sat, 01 Jan 2011 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://santandermetgroup.github.io/website-demo/event/2011-a-methodology-to-evaluate-regional-scale/</guid><description>&lt;p>The economic viability of offshore wind farms depends on the favorable wind conditions. It is, however, a challenge to study winds in the marine atmospheric environment. A common problem is the data collection since the wind dataset requires enough spatial and temporal resolution. Numerical hindcast (reanalysis) constitutes an alternative to disperse instrumental observations although two considerations should be studied in the reanalysis for regional purposes: the domain and the spatial resolution and a validation-calibration procedure using instrumental data. Accordingly, the wind resource process can be described by the following cascade activities: the coarse spatial wind fields from global meteorological experiments; the regional winds from a dynamic downscaling coupled to the global reanalysis fields; the validation and calibration procedures by using instrumental observations; and, finally, the characterization of winds for evaluation of the wind resource. This work proposes a methodology to study wind energy resources in a regional offshore area and shows the application along the offshore Spanish coast.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Analysing the multidimensional wave climate with self organizing maps</title><link>https://santandermetgroup.github.io/website-demo/event/2009-analysing-the-multidimensional-wave-climate/</link><pubDate>Thu, 01 Jan 2009 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://santandermetgroup.github.io/website-demo/event/2009-analysing-the-multidimensional-wave-climate/</guid><description>&lt;p>The term “wave climate” usually refers to the statistical distribution of several oceanographical geophysical variables. Components of the wave climate are variables such as wind velocity, W, wind direction, θW, significant wave height, Hs, peak period, Tp, and mean wave direction, θ. Usually, the classical analysis of the long-term distribution of wave climate is addressed using just one variable (f.i., long-term distribution of significant wave height) or at most bidimensionally (f.i., the bidimensional distribution of Hs and Tp). It is clear that the joint probability distribution of these five variables (Hs, Tp, θ, W, θW) is not easy to able to cope with. However, this problem is solved applying a non-linear clustering algorithm, namely the Self Organizing Maps (SOM), a neural network technique capable of classifying the high dimensional input reanalysis data in a low number of centroids (clusters) in an ordered sheet shape representation (Camus et al, 2007). The neurons are connected to adjacent elements by a neighbourhood relation. A multidimensional histogram of the sea state parameters is obtained allowing an easy further treatment of the classified sea states. &lt;/p>
&lt;p>Figure 1 shows a 23x23 SOM applied to a particular site located in Villano, Galicia (Spain). In this case, the original data space has been projected into a toroid lattice being the data accommodated in a circular way. This toroid shape has been again projected into the plane for a better visualization, separating the centroids which are located together, the centroids located in the upper side of the sheet are joined with the centroids&lt;br />
located on the lower side of the sheet and with the lateral sides in the 3D-dimension. Each cell of the SOM represents a cluster defined by the five parameters employed in the classification. The significant wave height, the wave period and the wave direction are represented by the size, the colour intensity and the direction of the arrow; the pink arrow represents the wind vector. The background of each hexagon has been filled in a blue scale, function of the frequency of occurrence. As it can be seen in the figure, this classification technique is capable of extracting all the possible sea states and the transition between them. The magnitudes of the parameters which define the centroids vary smoothly from one cell to another. The most energetic sea states present W-WNW&lt;br />
directions (i=17, j=14). The higher amount of data is grouped in clusters with low energy sea states (i=6, j=11). &lt;/p>
&lt;p>Figure 2 shows several SOMs for different locations along the northern coast of Spain. In this case, we are considering (Hs, Tp, θ) and a 10x10 SOM. In the presentation, the theoretical basis and some examples will show the ability of this methodology to describe the multidimensional wave climate.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>A methodology to evaluate wave energy resources in shallow waters</title><link>https://santandermetgroup.github.io/website-demo/event/2007-a-methodology-to-evaluate-wave/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 2007 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://santandermetgroup.github.io/website-demo/event/2007-a-methodology-to-evaluate-wave/</guid><description>&lt;p>A global frame for the determination of shallow water wave energy resources is developed. The methodology steps are: a) calibration of a wave reanalysis data base; b) classification of the sea states by means of the Self-Organizing Maps technique to obtain the number of sea states representatives of the wave climate in deep waters; c) propagation of the selected sea states using any state-ofthe-art wave propagation model and propagation of the whole reanalysis data base using an interpolation scheme; d) application of different statistical models to define energy resources.&lt;/p></description></item></channel></rss>