<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>Climate change | Santander Meteorology Group</title><link>https://santandermetgroup.github.io/website-demo/tag/climate-change/</link><atom:link href="https://santandermetgroup.github.io/website-demo/tag/climate-change/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><description>Climate change</description><generator>Wowchemy (https://wowchemy.com)</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Thu, 01 Jan 1970 00:33:32 +0000</lastBuildDate><image><url>https://santandermetgroup.github.io/website-demo/media/icon_hu58a305e0ce1458c8ebaf599b64640cde_12944_512x512_fill_lanczos_center_3.png</url><title>Climate change</title><link>https://santandermetgroup.github.io/website-demo/tag/climate-change/</link></image><item><title>A critical reassessment of statistical downscaling techniques under climate change conditions in Spain: Accuracy, distributional similarity and robustness</title><link>https://santandermetgroup.github.io/website-demo/event/2012-a-critical-reassessment-of-statistical/</link><pubDate>Thu, 01 Jan 1970 00:33:32 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://santandermetgroup.github.io/website-demo/event/2012-a-critical-reassessment-of-statistical/</guid><description>&lt;p>The performance of a wide range of statistical methods to downscale temperature (both maxima and minima) and precipitation in Spain is critically reassessed with respect to their robust applicability in climate change studies. For such purpose, we cross-validate the different techniques focusing on three distinct aspects: 1) accuracy (correlation, etc.), 2) distributional similarity (KS and PDF scores), and 3) stationarity/robustness under climate change conditions. For the latter, which is normally missed in state-of-the-art downscaling studies, we consider anomalous warm/cold (temperature) and dry/wet (precipitation) periods from the observational records - which serve as surrogates of possible future climate alterations - and test the performance of the methods, as compared to random periods. It is found that a near-perfect association between observed and downscaled series (e.g. high correlations) may hide important shortcomings in terms of distributional similarity and robustness. Therefore, a wide collection of downscaling configurations (domain-predictor-methodology) are evaluated in order to identify those being the most appropriate to deal with this issue.&lt;br />
This study is part of the work done in the project ESTCENA, a strategic action of Plan Nacional de I+D+i 2008-2011.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Assessing the robustness of statistical downscaling techniques for their application under climate change conditions</title><link>https://santandermetgroup.github.io/website-demo/event/2012-assessing-the-robustness-of-statistical/</link><pubDate>Thu, 01 Jan 1970 00:33:32 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://santandermetgroup.github.io/website-demo/event/2012-assessing-the-robustness-of-statistical/</guid><description>&lt;p>In this study, the applicability of statistical downscaling (SD) methods for use in climate change studies is assessed. To this aim, we introduce a new score to estimate the robustness of these methods to warming and drying climate conditions, as given by anomalously warm/dry years in the observational record. This score is applied to assess the relative performance of twelve different methods (from the analog, weather typing, weather generator, regression and GLM families) for downscaling temperatures and precipitation in Spain. Since the temperatures in the observed warm years are significantly underestimated by the analog and weather generator approaches, special care has to be taken when applying them to GCM scenario runs. This is demonstrated by relating the robustness-score to the mean relative warming obtained from applying the SD-methods to the A1B scenario run (2071-2100) from the ECHAM5 Global Climate Model.&lt;/p></description></item></channel></rss>