<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>species distribution models | Santander Meteorology Group</title><link>https://santandermetgroup.github.io/website-demo/tag/species-distribution-models/</link><atom:link href="https://santandermetgroup.github.io/website-demo/tag/species-distribution-models/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><description>species distribution models</description><generator>Wowchemy (https://wowchemy.com)</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Thu, 01 Jan 1970 00:33:36 +0000</lastBuildDate><image><url>https://santandermetgroup.github.io/website-demo/media/icon_hu58a305e0ce1458c8ebaf599b64640cde_12944_512x512_fill_lanczos_center_3.png</url><title>species distribution models</title><link>https://santandermetgroup.github.io/website-demo/tag/species-distribution-models/</link></image><item><title>Assessing the credibility of different species distribution models to project changes under future climate conditions</title><link>https://santandermetgroup.github.io/website-demo/event/2016-assessing-the-credibility-of-different/</link><pubDate>Thu, 01 Jan 1970 00:33:36 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://santandermetgroup.github.io/website-demo/event/2016-assessing-the-credibility-of-different/</guid><description>&lt;p>Species Distribution Models (SDMs) are widely applied to estimate future impacts on species distributions and assess key topics in environmental conservation. Future projections vary significantly depending on model algorithms and parameterizations, however, the evaluation of SDMs under future climate change is problematic, as events being predicted have yet not occurred. In front of the lack of an objective basis to perform a selection of various alternatives, we propose a method incorporating niche overlap metrics, for the selection of credible future projections under an ecologically meaningful basis. This method allows the discrimination of useful SDMs from ill-performing ones. In addition, given that the pseudo-absences used to train the model are known to have a significant impact on the results obtained, we analyse this source of uncertainty in future projections for each tested SDM. &lt;/p>
&lt;p>We apply the developed method on three phylogenies of pedunculate oak (Quercus robur L.) in Europe, considering three different modelling algorithms and a set of four state of the art regional-global climate model couplings , thus accounting for the main sources of uncertainty of future SDM projections. Finally, we calculate the range of probabilities of future projections obtained from models built for 10 runs of pseuso-absence data generation. Two pseudo-absence generation methods are compared, the commonly used random sampling (RS) and the improved Three-step method (TS).&lt;/p>
&lt;p>The niche overlap metric approach enabled an objective quality assessment of each individual SDM. The less complex algorithm (GLM) produced the most credible future projections. Contrarily, MARS (and to a lesser extent also MAXENT) projected the less credible future distributions due to model overfitting. The uncertainty related to pseudo-absence data was also lower for GLM, specially when the TS method was used. Therefore, we conclude that the use of a parsimonious algorithm is the best option in the context of future predictions.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>A new high resolution climate dataset in the Basque Country: Application for ecological niche modelling and future climate impact estimates</title><link>https://santandermetgroup.github.io/website-demo/event/2013-a-new-high-resolution-climate/</link><pubDate>Thu, 01 Jan 1970 00:33:33 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://santandermetgroup.github.io/website-demo/event/2013-a-new-high-resolution-climate/</guid><description>&lt;p>Global bioclimatic datasets are widely used in ecological research to estimate the potential distribution of species. Although these datasets offer high resolution information, they have not been tested rigorously in smaller regions, hence, it might not be appropriate to use them for the development of species distribution models (SDMs) due to their poor representation of local climate features. Moreover, this problem may be aggravated when predicting potential distributions in the future as a consequence of the uncertainty derived from the future altered climate scenarios. Faced with this problem a high resolution grid for the Basque Country has been developed as an alternative to existing public products: The Regional Baseline Climate of the Basque Country (RCBC). In this study we have modelled tree species under different climate datasets and SDM techniques in the Basque Country (Northern Iberian Peninsula), in order to compare the RCBC with the WorldClim bioclimatic dataset (WC) in a region of complex orography.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Adaptive variation, environmental gradients and demography in maritime pine: from genes to phenotypes and niches</title><link>https://santandermetgroup.github.io/website-demo/event/2013-adaptive-variation-environmental-gradients-and/</link><pubDate>Thu, 01 Jan 1970 00:33:33 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://santandermetgroup.github.io/website-demo/event/2013-adaptive-variation-environmental-gradients-and/</guid><description>&lt;p>Current and future species responses to predicted environmental changes are embedded in demographic and evolutionary processes that occurred in the past. Therefore, understanding range-wide patterns and interactions between environmental change, demography and evolution taking place in the past is essential for developing future management strategies.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Maritime pine, an ecologically and economically important tree species, lives in a highly heterogeneous environment, and is hence of great interest to assess its adaptive potential to foreseen changes in the Mediterranean forests, i.e. increase in aridity and recent land-use change. &lt;/p>
&lt;p>Combining various complementary approaches and looking at three distinct level of variation (gene, phenotype, and nice) we investigate adaptive patterns in this conifer at its distribution scale.&lt;/p></description></item></channel></rss>