<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>Statistical downscaling | Santander Meteorology Group</title><link>https://santandermetgroup.github.io/website-demo/tag/statistical-downscaling/</link><atom:link href="https://santandermetgroup.github.io/website-demo/tag/statistical-downscaling/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><description>Statistical downscaling</description><generator>Wowchemy (https://wowchemy.com)</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Fri, 01 Jan 2021 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><image><url>https://santandermetgroup.github.io/website-demo/media/icon_hu58a305e0ce1458c8ebaf599b64640cde_12944_512x512_fill_lanczos_center_3.png</url><title>Statistical downscaling</title><link>https://santandermetgroup.github.io/website-demo/tag/statistical-downscaling/</link></image><item><title>CORDyS | Contribution to the next generation of CORDEX regional climate projections: Dynamical and Statistical approaches</title><link>https://santandermetgroup.github.io/website-demo/project/cordys/</link><pubDate>Fri, 01 Jan 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://santandermetgroup.github.io/website-demo/project/cordys/</guid><description/></item><item><title>Added value of high resolution RCM simulations and comparison with Statistical Downscaling Methods within the EURO-CORDEX framework</title><link>https://santandermetgroup.github.io/website-demo/event/2016-added-value-of-high-resolution/</link><pubDate>Thu, 01 Jan 1970 00:33:36 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://santandermetgroup.github.io/website-demo/event/2016-added-value-of-high-resolution/</guid><description>&lt;p>High resolution Regional Climate Model (RCM) simulations and Statistical Downscaling Methods (SDMs) are important tools to provide the meteorological variables required in climate impact assessments. The present study analyzes two aspects that should be taken into account before using these methods in specific applications. First, we assess the added value of high resolution simulations from a EURO-CORDEX RCM ensemble. Secondly, RCMs are compared with SDMs, in order to show the merits and limitations of both downscaling techniques. Both aspects are assessed in terms of mean and extreme precipitation indices in Spain.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>The EURO-CORDEX initiative provides an appropriate framework for this study, since a common grid is used for all RCMs and the high and low resolution grids match each other at the grid cell boundaries. The ability of the high-resolution RCM simulations (0.11°) to represent observed precipitation is assessed at their skillful scale, by aggregating the 0.11° grid to the 0.44° resolution and evaluating the added value with respect to the low resolution (0.44°) runs. Since RCMs are prone to systematic biases, the added value of the high resolution runs is also analyzed after applying bias correction methods to the RCMs. Gridded observational products are available over the same grids as the RCMs, such as the Spain02 v4 family of EURO-CORDEX-compliant gridded datasets over Spain. Therefore, the evaluation of the RCMs and the development of the SDMs can be carried out on exactly the same grids, and SDMs produce a downscaling output comparable to the RCMs. A set of SDMs (namely analog resampling, weather typing and different versions of Generalized Linear Models) are applied using ERA-Interim predictor variables under a cross-validation approach.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Results show limited evidence for an added value of the high resolution RCM simulations in terms of seasonal mean biases. There is an indication of added value in the spatial patterns; however, this is not statistically significant after bias correcting both simulations.&lt;br />
The comparison of RCMs and SDMs based on specific precipitation-derived indices may not be fair as long as they are related to parameters that have been optimized in the calibration phase of SDMs. When the comparison is performed in terms of non-optimized parameters (e.g. dry spells), both downscaling techniques present similar skills and limitations.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Advantages and limitations of different statistical downscaling approaches for seasonal forecasting</title><link>https://santandermetgroup.github.io/website-demo/event/2016-advantages-and-limitations-of-different/</link><pubDate>Thu, 01 Jan 1970 00:33:36 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://santandermetgroup.github.io/website-demo/event/2016-advantages-and-limitations-of-different/</guid><description/></item><item><title>An intercomparison of a large ensemble of statistical downscaling methods for Europe: Overall results from the VALUE perfect predictor cross-validation experiment</title><link>https://santandermetgroup.github.io/website-demo/event/2016-an-intercomparison-of-a-large/</link><pubDate>Thu, 01 Jan 1970 00:33:36 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://santandermetgroup.github.io/website-demo/event/2016-an-intercomparison-of-a-large/</guid><description>&lt;p>VALUE is an open European network to validate and compare downscaling methods for climate change research (&lt;a href="http://www.value-cost.eu" title="http://www.value-cost.eu">http://www.value-cost.eu&lt;/a>). A key deliverable of VALUE is the development of a systematic validation framework to enable the assessment and comparison of both dynamical and statistical downscaling methods. This framework is based on a user-focused validation tree, guiding the selection of relevant validation indices and performance measures for different aspects of the validation (marginal, temporal, spatial, multi-variable). Moreover, several experiments have been designed to isolate specific points in the downscaling procedure where problems may occur (assessment of intrinsic performance, effect of errors inherited from the global models, effect of non-stationarity, etc.). The list of downscaling experiments includes 1) cross-validation with perfect predictors, 2) GCM predictors –aligned with EURO-CORDEX experiment– and 3) pseudo reality predictors (see Maraun et al. 2015, Earth’s Future, 3, doi:10.1002/2014EF000259, for more details). The results of these experiments are gathered, validated and publicly distributed through the VALUE validation portal, allowing for a comprehensive community-open downscaling intercomparison study.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>In this contribution we describe the overall results from Experiment 1), consisting of a European wide 5- fold cross-validation (with consecutive 6-year periods from 1979 to 2008) using predictors from ERA-Interim to downscale precipitation and temperatures (minimum and maximum) over a set of 86 ECA&amp;amp;D stations representative of the main geographical and climatic regions in Europe. As a result of the open call for contribution to this experiment (closed in Dec. 2015), over 40 methods representative of the main approaches (MOS and Perfect Prognosis, PP) and techniques (linear scaling, quantile mapping, analogs, weather typing, linear and generalized regression, weather generators, etc.) were submitted, including information both data (downscaled values) and metadata (characterizing different aspects of the downscaling methods). This constitutes the largest and most comprehensive to date intercomparison of statistical downscaling methods. Here, we present an overall validation, analyzing marginal and temporal aspects to assess the intrinsic performance and added value of statistical downscaling methods at both annual and seasonal levels. This validation takes into account the different properties/limitations of different approaches and techniques (as reported in the provided metadata) in order to perform a fair comparison. It is pointed out that this experiment alone is not sufficient to evaluate the limitations of (MOS) bias correction techniques. Moreover, it also does not fully validate PP since we don’t learn whether we have the right predictors and whether the PP assumption is valid. These problems will be analyzed in the subsequent community-open VALUE experiments 2) and 3), which will be open for participation along the present year.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Activities of the Santander MetGroup in relation to M5S, GCM, RCM, ESD and OBS</title><link>https://santandermetgroup.github.io/website-demo/event/2014-activities-of-the-santander-metgroup/</link><pubDate>Thu, 01 Jan 1970 00:33:34 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://santandermetgroup.github.io/website-demo/event/2014-activities-of-the-santander-metgroup/</guid><description>&lt;p>Summary of the Santander MetGroup activity, as hosting group of the workshop.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>A Comparison of Statistical, Dynamical and Combined MOS Downscaling Approaches in the Framework of the PNACC-2012 Spanish Program</title><link>https://santandermetgroup.github.io/website-demo/event/2013-a-comparison-of-statistical-dynamical/</link><pubDate>Thu, 01 Jan 1970 00:33:33 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://santandermetgroup.github.io/website-demo/event/2013-a-comparison-of-statistical-dynamical/</guid><description>&lt;p>In this work we present a comparison of dynamical and statistical (both perfect prognosis and Model Output Statistics, MOS) downscaling techniques focusing on maximum temperature and precipitation in the Iberian peninsula —a complex climate region with Atlantic, continental, and Mediterranean influences.— To this aim, the same forcing conditions (from ERA40 re- analysis data) are considered for all methods and a k- fold cross validation is conducted focusing on different validation scores. The methods are assessed not only in terms of accuracy and distributional similarity, but also considering their robustness/stationarity in changing climate conditions; to this aim, anomalous historical periods (warm/cold for maximum temperature and wet/dry for precipitation) are used as surrogates of possible future climate alterations, and differences with normal periods are tested using a standard Student t-test. As a result, the strengths and limitations of these techniques in terms of their robust applicability in climate change studies are reported.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>As most important results, the statistical/dynamical downscaling approaches show the best/worst performance in terms of accuracy and distributional similarity; however, MOS techniques are able to correct the deficiencies of the dynamical models according to the referece observations. However, the known limitations of the analogue method to reach unobserved values affect the robustness of statistical downscaling methods, mainly in the case of the maximum temperature, which are less robust than the dynamical ones.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Finally, we compare the 21st century regional projections for Spain obtained with the above methods in the framework of the Spanish Plan for Regional Climate Change Scenarios (PNACC-2012) showing that, when discarding nonrobust methods, both dynamical and statistical projections are in good agreement.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Ability of statistical and dynamical downscaling approaches to reproduce mean and heavy precipitation at different spatial scales over Europe</title><link>https://santandermetgroup.github.io/website-demo/event/2013-ability-of-statistical-and-dynamical/</link><pubDate>Thu, 01 Jan 1970 00:33:33 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://santandermetgroup.github.io/website-demo/event/2013-ability-of-statistical-and-dynamical/</guid><description>&lt;p>The present study compares statistical downscaling methods (SDMs) and dynamical downscaling with nested regional climate models (RCMs) at different target spatial scales over two European regions. All downscaling products were developed in the framework of Euro-CORDEX and use the ERA-Interim reanalysis as boundary conditions (in RCMs) and as large-scale predictor data (in SDMs). Downscaled precipitation is evaluated at two horizontal resolutions (0.11º and 0.44º) using simulations from the Euro-CORDEX RCM ensemble and SDS methods trained against gridded observational data. The objectives of the work are: (1) to compare both downscaling methodologies, to identify their respective strengths and weaknesses at (2) different spatial scales and considering (3) mean and heavy daily precipitation, and (4) to assess the impact of bias correction methods.&lt;br />
We focus on two target areas in Europe: Continental Spain and the European Alps, where high-resolution and high-quality gridded observational data sets are available. Moreover, these areas represent a variety of climate conditions. Over Spain, the Spain011/044 data sets are considered, which exactly match the Euro-CORDEX grid over Spain. The Alpine data set has been derived from the EURO4M gridded precipitation product provided by MeteoSwiss at 5km resolution. Observations were spatially averaged to match the Euro-CORDEX grid cells. In order to make the SDM results comparable, they were calibrated using the gridded observations as predictand and model performance was evaluated in a cross-validation framework. Bias correction methods and an additional SD step are applied to the RCM data to also incorporate observational information. The ability of the high-resolution RCM simulations (0.11°) to represent observed precipitation is furthermore assessed at their skillful scale, by aggregating the 0.11° grid to the 0.44° resolution and evaluating the added value with respect to the low resolution (0.44°) runs.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Assessing Fire Weather Index using statistical downscaling and spatial interpolation techniques in Greece</title><link>https://santandermetgroup.github.io/website-demo/event/2013-assessing-fire-weather-index-using/</link><pubDate>Thu, 01 Jan 1970 00:33:33 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://santandermetgroup.github.io/website-demo/event/2013-assessing-fire-weather-index-using/</guid><description>&lt;p>Forest fires have always been present in the Mediterranean ecosystems, thus they constitute a major ecological&lt;br />
and socio-economic issue. The last few decades though, the number of forest fires has significantly increased, as&lt;br />
well as their severity and impact on the environment. Local fire danger projections are often required when dealing&lt;br />
with wild fire research. In the present study the application of statistical downscaling and spatial interpolation&lt;br />
methods was performed to the Canadian Fire Weather Index (FWI), in order to assess forest fire risk in Greece.&lt;br />
The FWI is used worldwide (including the Mediterranean basin) to estimate the fire danger in a generalized fuel&lt;br />
type, based solely on weather observations. The meteorological inputs to the FWI System are noon values of&lt;br />
dry-bulb temperature, air relative humidity, 10m wind speed and precipitation during the previous 24 hours.&lt;br />
The statistical downscaling methods are based on a statistical model that takes into account empirical relationships&lt;br />
between large scale variables (used as predictors) and local scale variables. In the framework&lt;br />
of the current study the statistical downscaling portal developed by the Santander Meteorology Group&lt;br />
(&lt;a href="https://www.meteo.unican.es/downscaling" title="https://www.meteo.unican.es/downscaling">https://www.meteo.unican.es/downscaling&lt;/a>) in the framework of the EU project CLIMRUN (&lt;a href="http://www.climrun.eu" title="www.climrun.eu">www.climrun.eu&lt;/a>)&lt;br />
was used to downscale non standard parameters related to forest fire risk.&lt;br />
In this study, two different approaches were adopted. Firstly, the analogue downscaling technique was directly&lt;br />
performed to the FWI index values and secondly the same downscaling technique was performed indirectly through&lt;br />
the meteorological inputs of the index. In both cases, the statistical downscaling portal was used considering the&lt;br />
ERA-Interim reanalysis as predictands due to the lack of observations at noon.&lt;br />
Additionally, a three-dimensional (3D) interpolation method of position and elevation, based on Thin Plate Splines&lt;br />
(TPS) was used, to interpolate the ERA-Interim data used to calculate the index. Results from this method were&lt;br />
compared with the statistical downscaling results obtained from the portal.&lt;br />
Finally, FWI was computed using weather observations obtained from the Hellenic National Meteorological Service,&lt;br />
mainly in the south continental part of Greece and a comparison with the previous results was performed.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>A critical reassessment of statistical downscaling techniques under climate change conditions in Spain: Accuracy, distributional similarity and robustness</title><link>https://santandermetgroup.github.io/website-demo/event/2012-a-critical-reassessment-of-statistical/</link><pubDate>Thu, 01 Jan 1970 00:33:32 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://santandermetgroup.github.io/website-demo/event/2012-a-critical-reassessment-of-statistical/</guid><description>&lt;p>The performance of a wide range of statistical methods to downscale temperature (both maxima and minima) and precipitation in Spain is critically reassessed with respect to their robust applicability in climate change studies. For such purpose, we cross-validate the different techniques focusing on three distinct aspects: 1) accuracy (correlation, etc.), 2) distributional similarity (KS and PDF scores), and 3) stationarity/robustness under climate change conditions. For the latter, which is normally missed in state-of-the-art downscaling studies, we consider anomalous warm/cold (temperature) and dry/wet (precipitation) periods from the observational records - which serve as surrogates of possible future climate alterations - and test the performance of the methods, as compared to random periods. It is found that a near-perfect association between observed and downscaled series (e.g. high correlations) may hide important shortcomings in terms of distributional similarity and robustness. Therefore, a wide collection of downscaling configurations (domain-predictor-methodology) are evaluated in order to identify those being the most appropriate to deal with this issue.&lt;br />
This study is part of the work done in the project ESTCENA, a strategic action of Plan Nacional de I+D+i 2008-2011.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Assessing the robustness of statistical downscaling techniques for their application under climate change conditions</title><link>https://santandermetgroup.github.io/website-demo/event/2012-assessing-the-robustness-of-statistical/</link><pubDate>Thu, 01 Jan 1970 00:33:32 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://santandermetgroup.github.io/website-demo/event/2012-assessing-the-robustness-of-statistical/</guid><description>&lt;p>In this study, the applicability of statistical downscaling (SD) methods for use in climate change studies is assessed. To this aim, we introduce a new score to estimate the robustness of these methods to warming and drying climate conditions, as given by anomalously warm/dry years in the observational record. This score is applied to assess the relative performance of twelve different methods (from the analog, weather typing, weather generator, regression and GLM families) for downscaling temperatures and precipitation in Spain. Since the temperatures in the observed warm years are significantly underestimated by the analog and weather generator approaches, special care has to be taken when applying them to GCM scenario runs. This is demonstrated by relating the robustness-score to the mean relative warming obtained from applying the SD-methods to the A1B scenario run (2071-2100) from the ECHAM5 Global Climate Model.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Actual and future trends of extreme values of temperature for the NW Iberian Peninsula</title><link>https://santandermetgroup.github.io/website-demo/event/2009-actual-and-future-trends-of/</link><pubDate>Thu, 01 Jan 1970 00:33:29 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://santandermetgroup.github.io/website-demo/event/2009-actual-and-future-trends-of/</guid><description>&lt;p>It is now very well established that yearly averaged temperatures are increasing due to anthropogenic climate change. In the area of Galicia (NW Spain) this trend has also been determined. The main objective of this work is to assess actual and future trends of different extreme indices of temperature, which are of crucial importance for many impact studies.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>As direct GCM-output significantly underestimates the variance of daily surface temperature variables in NW Spain, these are obtained by applying a statistical downscaling technique (analog method), using 850hPa temperature and mean sea level pressure as combined predictors. The predictor fields have been extracted from a multi-model multi initial conditions ensemble of 14 runs of three GCMs participating in the IPCC AR4.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>For 1960-2006 results show a significant increase of the number of days with maximum temperatures above the 90th percentile. Furthermore, a significant decrease of the days with maximum temperatures below the 10th percentile has been found. The tendencies of minimum temperatures are reverse: less nights with minimum temperatures below the 10th percentile and more with minimum temperatures above 90th percentile. Those tendencies can be observed all over the year, but are more pronounced in summer. Results for relationship between the above mentioned extreme values and different North Atlantic teleconnection patterns show that local tendencies are associated with trends of EA (Eastern Atlantic) and SCA (Scandinavian) patterns. The NAO (North Atlantic Oscillation) only in winter is related to the number of cold days.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>The ensemble climate projections generated with the analog method indicate that the observed (linear) trends of maximum and minimum temperatures in NW Spain are expected to continue in the next decades. Furthermore the uncertainty interval of these projections (2021-2050) is dominated by model uncertainties rather than by forcing uncertainties.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>We conclude that more frequent hot days as well as an increasing probability of summertime heat waves are to be expected in the next decades. Cold days tend to diminish, decreasing the probability of wintertime cold waves and leaving a greater part of the area under study without frost throughout the year.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Aplicación de Métodos de Clasificación al Downscaling Estadístico</title><link>https://santandermetgroup.github.io/website-demo/event/2001-aplicacion-de-metodos-de-clasificacion/</link><pubDate>Thu, 01 Jan 1970 00:33:21 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://santandermetgroup.github.io/website-demo/event/2001-aplicacion-de-metodos-de-clasificacion/</guid><description>&lt;p>En este artículo se analizan diversas alternativas para la predicción probabilística de meteoros utilizando el método de análogos, y se presentan resultados de validación en la red principal de estaciones del INM en las diversas cuencas peninsulares. En primer lugar se comparan distintas especificaciones (tamaño de la rejilla y rango horario) del vector 4D que define el “estado de la atmósfera” en base a las predicciones de un modelo numérico. Seguidamente, se describe la forma más conveniente de comprimir esta información, eliminando redundancias, utilizando componentes principales. A continuación, se analizan distintas técnicas de clasificación para obtener un conjunto de estados de la atmósfera análogos a uno dado, de entre aquellos disponibles en una base de datos de estados históricos (reanálisis). Finalmente, se muestra la forma de mejorar la resolución de una predicción realizada por el modelo numérico a partir de la estadística de los meteoros locales observados en las fechas correspondientes a los análogos hallados para el estado definido por la predicción.&lt;/p></description></item></channel></rss>