<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>Jesús Fernández | Santander Meteorology Group</title><link>https://santandermetgroup.github.io/website-demo/author/jesus-fernandez/</link><atom:link href="https://santandermetgroup.github.io/website-demo/author/jesus-fernandez/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><description>Jesús Fernández</description><generator>Wowchemy (https://wowchemy.com)</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Tue, 29 Mar 2022 10:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><image><url>https://santandermetgroup.github.io/website-demo/author/jesus-fernandez/avatar_huc1dfee6a5bb46e2437b14af5e92e9fc7_151214_270x270_fill_q75_lanczos_center.jpg</url><title>Jesús Fernández</title><link>https://santandermetgroup.github.io/website-demo/author/jesus-fernandez/</link></image><item><title>Results from the EURO-CORDEX CMIP6 GCM selection task team</title><link>https://santandermetgroup.github.io/website-demo/event/220329_fernandez_medcordex/</link><pubDate>Tue, 29 Mar 2022 10:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://santandermetgroup.github.io/website-demo/event/220329_fernandez_medcordex/</guid><description/></item><item><title>Exploring the limits of the Jenkinson-Collison classification scheme for atmospheric circulation: A global assessment based on various reanalyses</title><link>https://santandermetgroup.github.io/website-demo/publication/fernandezg_cd_exploringlimits/</link><pubDate>Fri, 11 Mar 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://santandermetgroup.github.io/website-demo/publication/fernandezg_cd_exploringlimits/</guid><description>&lt;div class="alert alert-note">
&lt;div>
Click the &lt;em>Cite&lt;/em> button above to demo the feature to enable visitors to import publication metadata into their reference management software.
&lt;/div>
&lt;/div>
&lt;p>Supplementary notes can be added here, including &lt;a href="https://wowchemy.com/docs/content/writing-markdown-latex/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">code and math&lt;/a>.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>CORDyS | Contribution to the next generation of CORDEX regional climate projections: Dynamical and Statistical approaches</title><link>https://santandermetgroup.github.io/website-demo/project/cordys/</link><pubDate>Fri, 01 Jan 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://santandermetgroup.github.io/website-demo/project/cordys/</guid><description>&lt;p>The Coordinated Regional Climate Downscaling Experiment (CORDEX) initiative has been, for over a decade, the key international coordinating body in the production, scientific analysis and application of future climate projections at regional scale. This unfunded initiative provides a common framework for downscaling activities around the world. The ongoing second phase, focused on regional challenges through Flagship Pilot Studies (FPS) and the production of homogeneous information across the world (CORDEX-CORE), provides key regional climate information and science to the 6th Assessment Report of the Intergovernmental Panel on Climate Change (IPCC).&lt;/p>
&lt;p>The research team of this proposal has been involved in CORDEX activities since its inception. With the support of the Spanish National R&amp;amp;D Programme, we have contributed to CORDEX using dynamical downscaling through Regional Climate Models (RCMs; CORWES 2011-2014 and INSIGNIA 2017-2020) and statistical downscaling, including bias adjustment methods (MULTI-SDM 2016-2019). In this series of projects, we have developed downscaling tools, applied them in the different CORDEX phases, and actively participated in the coordinated science derived from them. This past activity has positioned the team as the only Spanish research group contributing future regional climate projections (European and South American domains at 0.44º) to the CORDEX ensemble, and the first to deploy in Spain a data node of the Earth System Grid Federation (ESGF), in charge of distributing CORDEX data, among others.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>CORDEX is currently facing the downscaling of CMIP6 global climate models (GCMs), which represent the latest generation of Coupled Earth System Models. The CORDyS project aims to contribute to this next generation of CORDEX regional climate projections using both dynamical and statistical downscaling methods, including statistical emulators of the dynamical models. Our objective is to contribute to (1) the process-based evaluation of the driving GCMs, (2) the downscaling of future climate projections for the current standard continental-scale CORDEX EUR-11 domain, (3) the further downscaling of future projections at very high resolution using a convection-permitting RCM and statistical emulators, (4) the distillation of actionable regional climate information for impacts assessment from these new-generation sources, and (5) the dissemination and publication of results and data products in the CORDEX community and ESGF infrastructure.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>These activities build on well-established previous efforts and contribute to the current forefront of CORDEX, positioning the group internationally and contributing to an initiative which returns climate information for, essentially, all projects and research groups working on regional climate research and other users assessing vulnerability, impacts and adaptation measures for future climate change at regional scales. At a national level, the results of this project will inform and contribute to Escenarios-PNACC (Plan Nacional de Adaptación al Cambio Climático), providing climate projections which build on the CORDEX experience and use the reference observational datasets.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Added value of high resolution RCM simulations and comparison with Statistical Downscaling Methods within the EURO-CORDEX framework</title><link>https://santandermetgroup.github.io/website-demo/event/2016-added-value-of-high-resolution/</link><pubDate>Fri, 01 Jan 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://santandermetgroup.github.io/website-demo/event/2016-added-value-of-high-resolution/</guid><description>&lt;p>High resolution Regional Climate Model (RCM) simulations and Statistical Downscaling Methods (SDMs) are important tools to provide the meteorological variables required in climate impact assessments. The present study analyzes two aspects that should be taken into account before using these methods in specific applications. First, we assess the added value of high resolution simulations from a EURO-CORDEX RCM ensemble. Secondly, RCMs are compared with SDMs, in order to show the merits and limitations of both downscaling techniques. Both aspects are assessed in terms of mean and extreme precipitation indices in Spain.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>The EURO-CORDEX initiative provides an appropriate framework for this study, since a common grid is used for all RCMs and the high and low resolution grids match each other at the grid cell boundaries. The ability of the high-resolution RCM simulations (0.11°) to represent observed precipitation is assessed at their skillful scale, by aggregating the 0.11° grid to the 0.44° resolution and evaluating the added value with respect to the low resolution (0.44°) runs. Since RCMs are prone to systematic biases, the added value of the high resolution runs is also analyzed after applying bias correction methods to the RCMs. Gridded observational products are available over the same grids as the RCMs, such as the Spain02 v4 family of EURO-CORDEX-compliant gridded datasets over Spain. Therefore, the evaluation of the RCMs and the development of the SDMs can be carried out on exactly the same grids, and SDMs produce a downscaling output comparable to the RCMs. A set of SDMs (namely analog resampling, weather typing and different versions of Generalized Linear Models) are applied using ERA-Interim predictor variables under a cross-validation approach.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Results show limited evidence for an added value of the high resolution RCM simulations in terms of seasonal mean biases. There is an indication of added value in the spatial patterns; however, this is not statistically significant after bias correcting both simulations.&lt;br />
The comparison of RCMs and SDMs based on specific precipitation-derived indices may not be fair as long as they are related to parameters that have been optimized in the calibration phase of SDMs. When the comparison is performed in terms of non-optimized parameters (e.g. dry spells), both downscaling techniques present similar skills and limitations.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>A set of regional climate change scenarios over Spain: ESCENA Project</title><link>https://santandermetgroup.github.io/website-demo/event/2015-a-set-of-regional-climate/</link><pubDate>Thu, 01 Jan 2015 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://santandermetgroup.github.io/website-demo/event/2015-a-set-of-regional-climate/</guid><description>&lt;p>ESCENA (&lt;a href="http://proyectoescena.uclm.es" title="http://proyectoescena.uclm.es">http://proyectoescena.uclm.es&lt;/a>) was part of the Spanish Strategic action on energy and&lt;br />
climate change. Funded by the Spanish government, this call aimed at providing the scientific basis&lt;br />
for the assessment of regional climate change impacts over Spain (including continental Spain, the&lt;br />
Balearic and Canary islands). The ESCENA project (2008-2011) agglutinated the regional climate&lt;br />
modelling efforts. Four different institutions contributed simulations using 4 different Regional Climate&lt;br />
Models (RCMs): Universidad de Castilla-La Mancha (UCLM, PROMES model), Universidad de&lt;br />
Murcia (UMUR, MM5 model), Universidad de Alcalá de Henares (UAHE, REMO model) and&lt;br />
Universidad de Cantabria (UCAN, WRF model).&lt;br />
The boundary forcing came from the Global Climate Model (GCM) simulations generated by the third&lt;br />
Coupled Model Intercomparison Project (CMIP3) for the 4th IPCC Assessment Report (AR4). We&lt;br />
used three different GCMs (ECHAM5-MPIOM, CNRM-CM3 and HadCM3) forced by the A1B, A2, and&lt;br />
B1 emissions scenarios. An interesting feature of the experimental setup in ESCENA was the&lt;br />
GCM/RCM matrix, which was designed to enable the comparison of different RCMs projections with a&lt;br />
single specific change (RCM, scenario, GCM, parameterization). This allows the exploration of the&lt;br />
role of different sources of uncertainty. The RCM simulations cover a common minimum domain&lt;br />
encompassing the whole Spanish territory with a horizontal resolution of 25 Km.&lt;br />
The project focused on the near future, simulating a control period (1950-2000, 1950 left as spin-up&lt;br />
and disregarded in the analyses) forced by the 20C3M historical scenario and continued by a 50-year&lt;br />
period, 2001-2050, of future projection. In this work we present the main results of the project,&lt;br />
focusing on the future climate projection scenarios for impact-relevant variables.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Assessing the role of regional climate models as intermediaries between global models and bias correction methods</title><link>https://santandermetgroup.github.io/website-demo/event/2015-assessing-the-role-of-regional/</link><pubDate>Thu, 01 Jan 2015 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://santandermetgroup.github.io/website-demo/event/2015-assessing-the-role-of-regional/</guid><description>&lt;p>Recently, the amount of publicly available future climate simulations has greatly increased, allowing for more robust climate change uncertainty assessments. However, the number of available experiments is strongly reduced when considering only computationally costly regional climate model (RCM) runs. These simulations are used as input for many impact studies, but usually after a statistical post-processing which takes into account the observations at station level (or very high resolution grids) and is commonly known as bias correction. These methods have been primarily developed for removing model biases, although they are also implicitly used to bridge the scale mismatch between model grids and local observations. &lt;/p>
&lt;p>Given that bias correction can be directly applied to Global Circulation Models (GCMs), we assess the role of RCMs as intermediaries between GCMs and bias correction methods. We apply different bias correction methods (from the simple scaling to different versions of the quantile-quantile mapping) directly to daily precipitation from a set of coarse resolution CMIP5 GCMs and compare them with bias-corrected EURO-CORDEX RCMs (namely COSMO-CLM and RCA at 12km horizontal resolution) for historical and future periods. We use a subset of European stations from the ECA&amp;amp;D dataset as observational reference for the bias correction. Additionally, a refined analysis in the Ebro catchment illustrates the effect of bias correction on spatial climate variability. &lt;/p>
&lt;p>The evaluation experiment of the historical simulations in a cross-validation framework shows that bias corrected RCMs and GCMs typically present similar biases, but an added value of RCMs is found for the spatial analysis. Second, the basic features and the overall magnitude of the climate change signal are preserved after applying bias correction, although in some cases the uncertainty in the climate change signal is amplified by bias correction.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Activities of the Santander MetGroup in relation to M5S, GCM, RCM, ESD and OBS</title><link>https://santandermetgroup.github.io/website-demo/event/2014-activities-of-the-santander-metgroup/</link><pubDate>Wed, 01 Jan 2014 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://santandermetgroup.github.io/website-demo/event/2014-activities-of-the-santander-metgroup/</guid><description>&lt;p>Summary of the Santander MetGroup activity, as hosting group of the workshop.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Assessing the drift of seasonal forecasts</title><link>https://santandermetgroup.github.io/website-demo/event/2014-assessing-the-drift-of-seasonal/</link><pubDate>Wed, 01 Jan 2014 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://santandermetgroup.github.io/website-demo/event/2014-assessing-the-drift-of-seasonal/</guid><description>&lt;p>The systematic drift (bias dependence on the forecast lead-time) present in state-of-the-art coupled general circulation models is an inherent feature of global seasonal forecasts. Usually, anomalies (relative to the model climatology) obtained from an ensemble of hindcasts are used to correct this drift. However, this procedure has not been systematically explored across different forecasting systems so far. Moreover, costly approaches for seasonal impacts forecasting, such as dynamical downscaling, would benefit from drift removal strategies involving smaller ensemble sizes.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>The full thirty-year (1981-2010) hindcast of the System 4 ECWMF (in particular the 15-members seasonal experiment) was considered to address these issues over two regions of interest for the EU project EUPORIAS, Europe and East Africa. The mean climatology for each calendar month was computed at seven different lead-times (each member was initialized the first of each month and was run for seven months). For instance,the climatology of January was computed considering the forecasts initialized the first of January (lead-month 0), December (lead-month 1) and so on until July (lead-month 6). Results show important drifts for some cases. Moreover, the differences between members are statistically not significant in general, what suggests that considering a single member may be enough to robustly remove the drift.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>In the near future, additional forecasting systems involved in EUPORIAS will be compared with System 4 in order to unveil possible commonalities in the drift climatology.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Ability of statistical and dynamical downscaling approaches to reproduce mean and heavy precipitation at different spatial scales over Europe</title><link>https://santandermetgroup.github.io/website-demo/event/2013-ability-of-statistical-and-dynamical/</link><pubDate>Tue, 01 Jan 2013 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://santandermetgroup.github.io/website-demo/event/2013-ability-of-statistical-and-dynamical/</guid><description>&lt;p>The present study compares statistical downscaling methods (SDMs) and dynamical downscaling with nested regional climate models (RCMs) at different target spatial scales over two European regions. All downscaling products were developed in the framework of Euro-CORDEX and use the ERA-Interim reanalysis as boundary conditions (in RCMs) and as large-scale predictor data (in SDMs). Downscaled precipitation is evaluated at two horizontal resolutions (0.11º and 0.44º) using simulations from the Euro-CORDEX RCM ensemble and SDS methods trained against gridded observational data. The objectives of the work are: (1) to compare both downscaling methodologies, to identify their respective strengths and weaknesses at (2) different spatial scales and considering (3) mean and heavy daily precipitation, and (4) to assess the impact of bias correction methods.&lt;br />
We focus on two target areas in Europe: Continental Spain and the European Alps, where high-resolution and high-quality gridded observational data sets are available. Moreover, these areas represent a variety of climate conditions. Over Spain, the Spain011/044 data sets are considered, which exactly match the Euro-CORDEX grid over Spain. The Alpine data set has been derived from the EURO4M gridded precipitation product provided by MeteoSwiss at 5km resolution. Observations were spatially averaged to match the Euro-CORDEX grid cells. In order to make the SDM results comparable, they were calibrated using the gridded observations as predictand and model performance was evaluated in a cross-validation framework. Bias correction methods and an additional SD step are applied to the RCM data to also incorporate observational information. The ability of the high-resolution RCM simulations (0.11°) to represent observed precipitation is furthermore assessed at their skillful scale, by aggregating the 0.11° grid to the 0.44° resolution and evaluating the added value with respect to the low resolution (0.44°) runs.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>A multi-physics ensemble over the CORDEX-Africa domain</title><link>https://santandermetgroup.github.io/website-demo/event/2012-a-multi-physics-ensemble-over-the/</link><pubDate>Sun, 01 Jan 2012 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://santandermetgroup.github.io/website-demo/event/2012-a-multi-physics-ensemble-over-the/</guid><description>&lt;p>WRF (Weather Research and Forecasting) model is a state of the art regional model whose use has spread worldwide. This kind of models solves the atmospheric circulation equations for a resolution higher than the Global Circulation Models (GCMs). Due to the coarse resolution of the latter, Regional Climate Models (RCMs) as WRF try to better represent climate for specific regions. WRF is a very flexible model and several different configurations can be selected changing the different parameterizations. For this reason, each configuration can be considered as a different model and the biases of the different configurations are as large as those corresponding to different RCMs (Vautard et al. 2012). Nowadays many research groups have run their own configurations, but analysing the sensitivity of the model to each configuration for each region is a relevant issue, since results can change significantly.&lt;br />
We focus our analysis on the African domain, which is the CORDEX priority. Our study is motivated by the need to find the best set of parameterizations for Africa concerning temperature and precipitation.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Assessment of extreme temperature percentiles by means of Regional Climate Models</title><link>https://santandermetgroup.github.io/website-demo/event/2012-assessment-of-extreme-temperature-percentiles/</link><pubDate>Sun, 01 Jan 2012 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://santandermetgroup.github.io/website-demo/event/2012-assessment-of-extreme-temperature-percentiles/</guid><description>&lt;p>The study of extreme events has become of great interest in the recent years due to their direct impact on society. Extremes can be evaluated both by using extreme value theory or deriving extreme indicators, which are usually based on statistics on the tail of the probability distribution. Some of the most commonly used indicators are based on percentiles. In this study we calculate the most extreme percentiles in maximum (90p, 95p and 99p) and minimum (1p, 5p and 10p) temperature derived from the application of dynamical downscaling methods in the Iberian Peninsula. We analyze the regional climate models (RCMs) of the ENSEMBLES (EU-funded) and ESCENA (strategic action of Plan Nacional de I+D+i 2008-2011 funded by the Spanish government) projects.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>The dynamical downscaling methods are first tested in present climate with quasi-perfect (reanalysis) boundary conditions in order to know to what extent these approaches properly reproduce the observed percentiles. Then, we analyze the effect of nesting the RCMs to different Global Circulation Models (GCMs) on the 20C3M scenario. The study focuses on the end of the 20th century (1961–2000), used as a reference period, and assesses the changes projected for the period 2031–2050 considering the A1B emission scenario.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>The comparison among the different models is obtained in terms of both the annual and seasonal biases. Analyzing the bias patterns, we are able to know whether the inter-RCM variability leads to larger biases than those due to the driving GCM. Moreover, due to the sensitivity of the results to the observational dataset used for the comparison, we consider the new, public, gridded dataset developed for continental Spain and Balearic Islands with 0.2º resolution (Spain02; Herrera et al. 2012).&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Herrera, S., Gutierrez, J., Ancell, R., Pons, M., Frias, M., and Fernandez, J.: Development and Analysis of a 50 year high-resolution daily gridded precipitation dataset over Spain (Spain02). International Journal of Climatology 32:74-85 DOI: 10.1002/joc.2256 .&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>A methodology to evaluate regional-scale offshore wind energy resources.</title><link>https://santandermetgroup.github.io/website-demo/event/2011-a-methodology-to-evaluate-regional-scale/</link><pubDate>Sat, 01 Jan 2011 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://santandermetgroup.github.io/website-demo/event/2011-a-methodology-to-evaluate-regional-scale/</guid><description>&lt;p>The economic viability of offshore wind farms depends on the favorable wind conditions. It is, however, a challenge to study winds in the marine atmospheric environment. A common problem is the data collection since the wind dataset requires enough spatial and temporal resolution. Numerical hindcast (reanalysis) constitutes an alternative to disperse instrumental observations although two considerations should be studied in the reanalysis for regional purposes: the domain and the spatial resolution and a validation-calibration procedure using instrumental data. Accordingly, the wind resource process can be described by the following cascade activities: the coarse spatial wind fields from global meteorological experiments; the regional winds from a dynamic downscaling coupled to the global reanalysis fields; the validation and calibration procedures by using instrumental observations; and, finally, the characterization of winds for evaluation of the wind resource. This work proposes a methodology to study wind energy resources in a regional offshore area and shows the application along the offshore Spanish coast.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>A cloud-computing system on the grid through virtualization</title><link>https://santandermetgroup.github.io/website-demo/event/2009-a-cloud-computing-system-on-the/</link><pubDate>Thu, 01 Jan 2009 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://santandermetgroup.github.io/website-demo/event/2009-a-cloud-computing-system-on-the/</guid><description>&lt;p>Nowadays, scientists who make use of the grid are experiencing incompatibility problems between the scientific application that is executed on Working Nodes (WN) and the software installed on them; such as operating system, libraries, and grid middleware. On the other hand, scientists have problems to submit their jobs to different grid sites, because of the grid does not provide a software installation standard on them. This work presents the integration of virtualization technology on grid WN's. This way, users can introduce an application into a virtual machine (VM) with different software to the one installed on the WN. Thus, the job submitted by the user, will cause the VM to start on a WN of some site and to automatically execute a scientific application that may have been previously prepared in a user friendly environment. This work, which is based on the cloud computing notion, lets the users to execute applications on the grid, in isolation from lower software layers. Results have achieved the expected objective: to let users submit scientific applications to the grid, isolating application dependences from the grid software environment.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Analysis of Extreme Temperatures in Iberia: Observations and RCM Simulations from the ENSEMBLES Project</title><link>https://santandermetgroup.github.io/website-demo/event/2009-analysis-of-extreme-temperatures-in/</link><pubDate>Thu, 01 Jan 2009 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://santandermetgroup.github.io/website-demo/event/2009-analysis-of-extreme-temperatures-in/</guid><description>&lt;p>The study of climate extremes is an active research topic with huge socioeconomic impacts (see Easterling et al 2000 and references therein). Most of the results published in the literature are based on univariate GEV or POT models, applied to either observations (Brown et al. 2008) or global (Goubana and Li, 2007) and regional (Frei et al. 2006) simulations. These studies have reported different trends in the temperature and precipitation extremes for the 20th century and future climate scenarios in different regions of interest. In the present work, we use state-of-the-art observed and simulated data over Europe, developed in the ENSEMBLES project (&lt;a href="http://www.ensembles-eu.org" title="www.ensembles-eu.org">www.ensembles-eu.org&lt;/a>), to analyze and compare the observed and simulated temperature extremes in the Iberian peninsula. In particular, we consider the ENSEMBLES gridded observations and the ensemble of RCM simulations with a common resolution of 25km. In the future, we plan to study the effect of spatial dependence in the obtained results using appropriate multivariate techniques.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>References:&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Brown, S. J., J. Caesar, and C. A. T. Ferro (2008), Global changes in extreme daily temperature since 1950, J. Geophys. Res., 113, D05115,&lt;br />
doi:10.1029/2006JD008091.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Easterling, D. R. and G. A. Meehl and C. Parmesan and S. A. Changnon and T. R. Karl and L. O. Mearns (2000) Climate Extremes: Observations, Climate Extremes: Observations, Modeling, and Impacts. Science  289,  2068-2074.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Frei, C., R. Schöll, S. Fukutome, J. Schmidli, and P. L. Vidale (2006), Future change of precipitation extremes in Europe: Intercomparison of&lt;br />
scenarios from regional climate models, J. Geophys. Res., 111, D06105, doi:10.1029/2005JD005965.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Goubanova, K. and L. Li (2007) Extremes in temperature and precipitation around the Mediterranean basin in an ensemble of future climate scenario simulation. Global and Planetary Change, 57, 27-42.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Aplicaciones en Ciencias de la Tierra: vo.meteo.es-ngi.eu</title><link>https://santandermetgroup.github.io/website-demo/event/2009-aplicaciones-en-ciencias-de-la/</link><pubDate>Thu, 01 Jan 2009 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://santandermetgroup.github.io/website-demo/event/2009-aplicaciones-en-ciencias-de-la/</guid><description>&lt;p>Revisón de la situación actual del Área de Aplicaciones, concretamente Ciencias de a Tierra, en la Red Española de eCiencia. En esta presentación se repasa las actividades realizadas durante el último año de las aplicaciones y pilotos desplegadas en la Red, y concretamene la creación de la VO vo.meteo.es-ngi.eu.&lt;/p></description></item></channel></rss>