<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>Jesús Fernández | Santander Meteorology Group</title><link>https://santandermetgroup.github.io/website-demo/author/jesus-fernandez/</link><atom:link href="https://santandermetgroup.github.io/website-demo/author/jesus-fernandez/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><description>Jesús Fernández</description><generator>Wowchemy (https://wowchemy.com)</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Tue, 29 Mar 2022 10:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><image><url>https://santandermetgroup.github.io/website-demo/author/jesus-fernandez/avatar_huc1dfee6a5bb46e2437b14af5e92e9fc7_151214_270x270_fill_q75_lanczos_center.jpg</url><title>Jesús Fernández</title><link>https://santandermetgroup.github.io/website-demo/author/jesus-fernandez/</link></image><item><title>Results from the EURO-CORDEX CMIP6 GCM selection task team</title><link>https://santandermetgroup.github.io/website-demo/event/220329_fernandez_medcordex/</link><pubDate>Tue, 29 Mar 2022 10:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://santandermetgroup.github.io/website-demo/event/220329_fernandez_medcordex/</guid><description>&lt;p>Slides can be added in a few ways:&lt;/p>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>Create&lt;/strong> slides using Wowchemy&amp;rsquo;s &lt;a href="https://wowchemy.com/docs/managing-content/#create-slides" target="_blank" rel="noopener">&lt;em>Slides&lt;/em>&lt;/a> feature and link using &lt;code>slides&lt;/code> parameter in the front matter of the talk file&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>Upload&lt;/strong> an existing slide deck to &lt;code>static/&lt;/code> and link using &lt;code>url_slides&lt;/code> parameter in the front matter of the talk file&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>Embed&lt;/strong> your slides (e.g. Google Slides) or presentation video on this page using &lt;a href="https://wowchemy.com/docs/writing-markdown-latex/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">shortcodes&lt;/a>.&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;p>Further event details, including page elements such as image galleries, can be added to the body of this page.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Exploring the limits of the Jenkinson-Collison classification scheme for atmospheric circulation: A global assessment based on various reanalyses</title><link>https://santandermetgroup.github.io/website-demo/publication/fernandezg_cd_exploringlimits/</link><pubDate>Fri, 11 Mar 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://santandermetgroup.github.io/website-demo/publication/fernandezg_cd_exploringlimits/</guid><description>&lt;div class="alert alert-note">
&lt;div>
Click the &lt;em>Cite&lt;/em> button above to demo the feature to enable visitors to import publication metadata into their reference management software.
&lt;/div>
&lt;/div>
&lt;p>Supplementary notes can be added here, including &lt;a href="https://wowchemy.com/docs/content/writing-markdown-latex/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">code and math&lt;/a>.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Analysis of Extreme Temperatures in Iberia: Observations and RCM Simulations from the ENSEMBLES Project</title><link>https://santandermetgroup.github.io/website-demo/event/2009-analysis-of-extreme-temperatures-in/</link><pubDate>Thu, 01 Jan 2009 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://santandermetgroup.github.io/website-demo/event/2009-analysis-of-extreme-temperatures-in/</guid><description>&lt;p>The study of climate extremes is an active research topic with huge socioeconomic impacts (see Easterling et al 2000 and references therein). Most of the results published in the literature are based on univariate GEV or POT models, applied to either observations (Brown et al. 2008) or global (Goubana and Li, 2007) and regional (Frei et al. 2006) simulations. These studies have reported different trends in the temperature and precipitation extremes for the 20th century and future climate scenarios in different regions of interest. In the present work, we use state-of-the-art observed and simulated data over Europe, developed in the ENSEMBLES project (&lt;a href="http://www.ensembles-eu.org" title="www.ensembles-eu.org">www.ensembles-eu.org&lt;/a>), to analyze and compare the observed and simulated temperature extremes in the Iberian peninsula. In particular, we consider the ENSEMBLES gridded observations and the ensemble of RCM simulations with a common resolution of 25km. In the future, we plan to study the effect of spatial dependence in the obtained results using appropriate multivariate techniques.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>References:&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Brown, S. J., J. Caesar, and C. A. T. Ferro (2008), Global changes in extreme daily temperature since 1950, J. Geophys. Res., 113, D05115,&lt;br />
doi:10.1029/2006JD008091.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Easterling, D. R. and G. A. Meehl and C. Parmesan and S. A. Changnon and T. R. Karl and L. O. Mearns (2000) Climate Extremes: Observations, Climate Extremes: Observations, Modeling, and Impacts. Science  289,  2068-2074.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Frei, C., R. Schöll, S. Fukutome, J. Schmidli, and P. L. Vidale (2006), Future change of precipitation extremes in Europe: Intercomparison of&lt;br />
scenarios from regional climate models, J. Geophys. Res., 111, D06105, doi:10.1029/2005JD005965.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Goubanova, K. and L. Li (2007) Extremes in temperature and precipitation around the Mediterranean basin in an ensemble of future climate scenario simulation. Global and Planetary Change, 57, 27-42.&lt;/p></description></item></channel></rss>