<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>Precipitation | Santander Meteorology Group</title><link>https://santandermetgroup.github.io/website-demo/tag/precipitation/</link><atom:link href="https://santandermetgroup.github.io/website-demo/tag/precipitation/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><description>Precipitation</description><generator>Wowchemy (https://wowchemy.com)</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Wed, 05 Oct 2016 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><image><url>https://santandermetgroup.github.io/website-demo/media/icon_hu58a305e0ce1458c8ebaf599b64640cde_12944_512x512_fill_lanczos_center_3.png</url><title>Precipitation</title><link>https://santandermetgroup.github.io/website-demo/tag/precipitation/</link></image><item><title>Advantages and limitations of different statistical downscaling approaches for seasonal forecasting</title><link>https://santandermetgroup.github.io/website-demo/event/2016-advantages-and-limitations-of-different/</link><pubDate>Wed, 05 Oct 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://santandermetgroup.github.io/website-demo/event/2016-advantages-and-limitations-of-different/</guid><description/></item><item><title>Added value of high resolution RCM simulations and comparison with Statistical Downscaling Methods within the EURO-CORDEX framework</title><link>https://santandermetgroup.github.io/website-demo/event/2016-added-value-of-high-resolution/</link><pubDate>Tue, 17 May 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://santandermetgroup.github.io/website-demo/event/2016-added-value-of-high-resolution/</guid><description>&lt;p>High resolution Regional Climate Model (RCM) simulations and Statistical Downscaling Methods (SDMs) are important tools to provide the meteorological variables required in climate impact assessments. The present study analyzes two aspects that should be taken into account before using these methods in specific applications. First, we assess the added value of high resolution simulations from a EURO-CORDEX RCM ensemble. Secondly, RCMs are compared with SDMs, in order to show the merits and limitations of both downscaling techniques. Both aspects are assessed in terms of mean and extreme precipitation indices in Spain.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>The EURO-CORDEX initiative provides an appropriate framework for this study, since a common grid is used for all RCMs and the high and low resolution grids match each other at the grid cell boundaries. The ability of the high-resolution RCM simulations (0.11째) to represent observed precipitation is assessed at their skillful scale, by aggregating the 0.11째 grid to the 0.44째 resolution and evaluating the added value with respect to the low resolution (0.44째) runs. Since RCMs are prone to systematic biases, the added value of the high resolution runs is also analyzed after applying bias correction methods to the RCMs. Gridded observational products are available over the same grids as the RCMs, such as the Spain02 v4 family of EURO-CORDEX-compliant gridded datasets over Spain. Therefore, the evaluation of the RCMs and the development of the SDMs can be carried out on exactly the same grids, and SDMs produce a downscaling output comparable to the RCMs. A set of SDMs (namely analog resampling, weather typing and different versions of Generalized Linear Models) are applied using ERA-Interim predictor variables under a cross-validation approach.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Results show limited evidence for an added value of the high resolution RCM simulations in terms of seasonal mean biases. There is an indication of added value in the spatial patterns; however, this is not statistically significant after bias correcting both simulations.
The comparison of RCMs and SDMs based on specific precipitation-derived indices may not be fair as long as they are related to parameters that have been optimized in the calibration phase of SDMs. When the comparison is performed in terms of non-optimized parameters (e.g. dry spells), both downscaling techniques present similar skills and limitations.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>A critical reassessment of statistical downscaling techniques under climate change conditions in Spain: Accuracy, distributional similarity and robustness</title><link>https://santandermetgroup.github.io/website-demo/event/2012-a-critical-reassessment-of-statistical/</link><pubDate>Tue, 25 Sep 2012 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://santandermetgroup.github.io/website-demo/event/2012-a-critical-reassessment-of-statistical/</guid><description>&lt;p>The performance of a wide range of statistical methods to downscale temperature (both maxima and minima) and precipitation in Spain is critically reassessed with respect to their robust applicability in climate change studies. For such purpose, we cross-validate the different techniques focusing on three distinct aspects: 1) accuracy (correlation, etc.), 2) distributional similarity (KS and PDF scores), and 3) stationarity/robustness under climate change conditions. For the latter, which is normally missed in state-of-the-art downscaling studies, we consider anomalous warm/cold (temperature) and dry/wet (precipitation) periods from the observational records - which serve as surrogates of possible future climate alterations - and test the performance of the methods, as compared to random periods. It is found that a near-perfect association between observed and downscaled series (e.g. high correlations) may hide important shortcomings in terms of distributional similarity and robustness. Therefore, a wide collection of downscaling configurations (domain-predictor-methodology) are evaluated in order to identify those being the most appropriate to deal with this issue.
This study is part of the work done in the project ESTCENA, a strategic action of Plan Nacional de I+D+i 2008-2011.&lt;/p></description></item></channel></rss>