<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>Statistical downscaling and local weather forecast | Santander Meteorology Group</title><link>https://santandermetgroup.github.io/website-demo/research_lines/statistical-downscaling-and-local-weather-forecast/</link><atom:link href="https://santandermetgroup.github.io/website-demo/research_lines/statistical-downscaling-and-local-weather-forecast/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><description>Statistical downscaling and local weather forecast</description><generator>Wowchemy (https://wowchemy.com)</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Wed, 05 Oct 2016 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><image><url>https://santandermetgroup.github.io/website-demo/media/icon_hu58a305e0ce1458c8ebaf599b64640cde_12944_512x512_fill_lanczos_center_3.png</url><title>Statistical downscaling and local weather forecast</title><link>https://santandermetgroup.github.io/website-demo/research_lines/statistical-downscaling-and-local-weather-forecast/</link></image><item><title>Advantages and limitations of different statistical downscaling approaches for seasonal forecasting</title><link>https://santandermetgroup.github.io/website-demo/event/2016-advantages-and-limitations-of-different/</link><pubDate>Wed, 05 Oct 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://santandermetgroup.github.io/website-demo/event/2016-advantages-and-limitations-of-different/</guid><description/></item><item><title>An intercomparison of a large ensemble of statistical downscaling methods for Europe: Overall results from the VALUE perfect predictor cross-validation experiment</title><link>https://santandermetgroup.github.io/website-demo/event/2016-an-intercomparison-of-a-large/</link><pubDate>Sun, 17 Apr 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://santandermetgroup.github.io/website-demo/event/2016-an-intercomparison-of-a-large/</guid><description>&lt;p>VALUE is an open European network to validate and compare downscaling methods for climate change research (&lt;a href="http://www.value-cost.eu" target="_blank" rel="noopener">http://www.value-cost.eu&lt;/a>). A key deliverable of VALUE is the development of a systematic validation framework to enable the assessment and comparison of both dynamical and statistical downscaling methods. This framework is based on a user-focused validation tree, guiding the selection of relevant validation indices and performance measures for different aspects of the validation (marginal, temporal, spatial, multi-variable). Moreover, several experiments have been designed to isolate specific points in the downscaling procedure where problems may occur (assessment of intrinsic performance, effect of errors inherited from the global models, effect of non-stationarity, etc.). The list of downscaling experiments includes 1) cross-validation with perfect predictors, 2) GCM predictors –aligned with EURO-CORDEX experiment– and 3) pseudo reality predictors (see Maraun et al. 2015, Earth’s Future, 3, doi:10.1002/2014EF000259, for more details). The results of these experiments are gathered, validated and publicly distributed through the VALUE validation portal, allowing for a comprehensive community-open downscaling intercomparison study.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>In this contribution we describe the overall results from Experiment 1), consisting of a European wide 5- fold cross-validation (with consecutive 6-year periods from 1979 to 2008) using predictors from ERA-Interim to downscale precipitation and temperatures (minimum and maximum) over a set of 86 ECA&amp;amp;D stations representative of the main geographical and climatic regions in Europe. As a result of the open call for contribution to this experiment (closed in Dec. 2015), over 40 methods representative of the main approaches (MOS and Perfect Prognosis, PP) and techniques (linear scaling, quantile mapping, analogs, weather typing, linear and generalized regression, weather generators, etc.) were submitted, including information both data (downscaled values) and metadata (characterizing different aspects of the downscaling methods). This constitutes the largest and most comprehensive to date intercomparison of statistical downscaling methods. Here, we present an overall validation, analyzing marginal and temporal aspects to assess the intrinsic performance and added value of statistical downscaling methods at both annual and seasonal levels. This validation takes into account the different properties/limitations of different approaches and techniques (as reported in the provided metadata) in order to perform a fair comparison. It is pointed out that this experiment alone is not sufficient to evaluate the limitations of (MOS) bias correction techniques. Moreover, it also does not fully validate PP since we don’t learn whether we have the right predictors and whether the PP assumption is valid. These problems will be analyzed in the subsequent community-open VALUE experiments 2) and 3), which will be open for participation along the present year.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Activities of the Santander MetGroup in relation to M5S, GCM, RCM, ESD and OBS</title><link>https://santandermetgroup.github.io/website-demo/event/2014-activities-of-the-santander-metgroup/</link><pubDate>Wed, 29 Oct 2014 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://santandermetgroup.github.io/website-demo/event/2014-activities-of-the-santander-metgroup/</guid><description>&lt;p>Summary of the Santander MetGroup activity, as hosting group of the workshop.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>A Comparison of Statistical, Dynamical and Combined MOS Downscaling Approaches in the Framework of the PNACC-2012 Spanish Program</title><link>https://santandermetgroup.github.io/website-demo/event/2013-a-comparison-of-statistical-dynamical/</link><pubDate>Mon, 04 Nov 2013 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://santandermetgroup.github.io/website-demo/event/2013-a-comparison-of-statistical-dynamical/</guid><description>&lt;p>In this work we present a comparison of dynamical and statistical (both perfect prognosis and Model Output Statistics, MOS) downscaling techniques focusing on maximum temperature and precipitation in the Iberian peninsula —a complex climate region with Atlantic, continental, and Mediterranean influences.— To this aim, the same forcing conditions (from ERA40 re- analysis data) are considered for all methods and a k- fold cross validation is conducted focusing on different validation scores. The methods are assessed not only in terms of accuracy and distributional similarity, but also considering their robustness/stationarity in changing climate conditions; to this aim, anomalous historical periods (warm/cold for maximum temperature and wet/dry for precipitation) are used as surrogates of possible future climate alterations, and differences with normal periods are tested using a standard Student t-test. As a result, the strengths and limitations of these techniques in terms of their robust applicability in climate change studies are reported.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>As most important results, the statistical/dynamical downscaling approaches show the best/worst performance in terms of accuracy and distributional similarity; however, MOS techniques are able to correct the deficiencies of the dynamical models according to the referece observations. However, the known limitations of the analogue method to reach unobserved values affect the robustness of statistical downscaling methods, mainly in the case of the maximum temperature, which are less robust than the dynamical ones.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Finally, we compare the 21st century regional projections for Spain obtained with the above methods in the framework of the Spanish Plan for Regional Climate Change Scenarios (PNACC-2012) showing that, when discarding nonrobust methods, both dynamical and statistical projections are in good agreement.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Assessing Fire Weather Index using statistical downscaling and spatial interpolation techniques in Greece</title><link>https://santandermetgroup.github.io/website-demo/event/2013-assessing-fire-weather-index-using/</link><pubDate>Sun, 07 Apr 2013 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://santandermetgroup.github.io/website-demo/event/2013-assessing-fire-weather-index-using/</guid><description>&lt;p>Forest fires have always been present in the Mediterranean ecosystems, thus they constitute a major ecological
and socio-economic issue. The last few decades though, the number of forest fires has significantly increased, as
well as their severity and impact on the environment. Local fire danger projections are often required when dealing
with wild fire research. In the present study the application of statistical downscaling and spatial interpolation
methods was performed to the Canadian Fire Weather Index (FWI), in order to assess forest fire risk in Greece.
The FWI is used worldwide (including the Mediterranean basin) to estimate the fire danger in a generalized fuel
type, based solely on weather observations. The meteorological inputs to the FWI System are noon values of
dry-bulb temperature, air relative humidity, 10m wind speed and precipitation during the previous 24 hours.
The statistical downscaling methods are based on a statistical model that takes into account empirical relationships
between large scale variables (used as predictors) and local scale variables. In the framework
of the current study the statistical downscaling portal developed by the Santander Meteorology Group
(&lt;a href="https://www.meteo.unican.es/downscaling" target="_blank" rel="noopener">https://www.meteo.unican.es/downscaling&lt;/a>) in the framework of the EU project CLIMRUN (&lt;a href="https://www.climrun.eu" target="_blank" rel="noopener">www.climrun.eu&lt;/a>)
was used to downscale non standard parameters related to forest fire risk.
In this study, two different approaches were adopted. Firstly, the analogue downscaling technique was directly
performed to the FWI index values and secondly the same downscaling technique was performed indirectly through
the meteorological inputs of the index. In both cases, the statistical downscaling portal was used considering the
ERA-Interim reanalysis as predictands due to the lack of observations at noon.
Additionally, a three-dimensional (3D) interpolation method of position and elevation, based on Thin Plate Splines
(TPS) was used, to interpolate the ERA-Interim data used to calculate the index. Results from this method were
compared with the statistical downscaling results obtained from the portal.
Finally, FWI was computed using weather observations obtained from the Hellenic National Meteorological Service,
mainly in the south continental part of Greece and a comparison with the previous results was performed.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>A new source of seasonal predictability for the winter climate in Spain</title><link>https://santandermetgroup.github.io/website-demo/event/2012-a-new-source-of-seasonal/</link><pubDate>Tue, 25 Sep 2012 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://santandermetgroup.github.io/website-demo/event/2012-a-new-source-of-seasonal/</guid><description>&lt;p>In a previously published study (Cohen &amp;amp; Jones 2011), an index describing the increase of Eurasian snow cover during October (Snow Advance Index, SAI) has shown to be associated with the Arctic Oscillation (AO) in the following winter (DJF). Based on this finding, we demonstrate that a modified version of the October SAI is highly correlated with the DJF-mean North Atlantic Oscillation, as well as with the concurrent values for precipitation, insolation and wind speed over Spain. Exploiting this formerly unknown lagged teleconnection, a statistical forecasting scheme is applied to predict the above mentioned variables one month ahead. The hindcast skill obtained from a one-year out cross-validation considerably outperforms the results of any competing dynamical and empirical forecasting approach available to date.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Reference&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Brands S, Manzanas R, Gutiérrez JM, Cohen J (2012): Seasonal Predictability of Wintertime Precipitation in Europe Using the Snow Advance Index. Journal of Climate 25:4023-4028&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Cohen J, Jones J (2011) A new index for more accurate winter predictions. Geophyiscal Research Letters 38:L21701, doi:10.1029/2011GL049626&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Analysing the multidimensional wave climate with self organizing maps</title><link>https://santandermetgroup.github.io/website-demo/event/2009-analysing-the-multidimensional-wave-climate/</link><pubDate>Mon, 11 May 2009 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://santandermetgroup.github.io/website-demo/event/2009-analysing-the-multidimensional-wave-climate/</guid><description>&lt;p>The term “wave climate” usually refers to the statistical distribution of several oceanographical geophysical variables. Components of the wave climate are variables such as wind velocity, W, wind direction, θW, significant wave height, Hs, peak period, Tp, and mean wave direction, θ. Usually, the classical analysis of the long-term distribution of wave climate is addressed using just one variable (f.i., long-term distribution of significant wave height) or at most bidimensionally (f.i., the bidimensional distribution of Hs and Tp). It is clear that the joint probability distribution of these five variables (Hs, Tp, θ, W, θW) is not easy to able to cope with. However, this problem is solved applying a non-linear clustering algorithm, namely the Self Organizing Maps (SOM), a neural network technique capable of classifying the high dimensional input reanalysis data in a low number of centroids (clusters) in an ordered sheet shape representation (Camus et al, 2007). The neurons are connected to adjacent elements by a neighbourhood relation. A multidimensional histogram of the sea state parameters is obtained allowing an easy further treatment of the classified sea states.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Figure 1 shows a 23x23 SOM applied to a particular site located in Villano, Galicia (Spain). In this case, the original data space has been projected into a toroid lattice being the data accommodated in a circular way. This toroid shape has been again projected into the plane for a better visualization, separating the centroids which are located together, the centroids located in the upper side of the sheet are joined with the centroids
located on the lower side of the sheet and with the lateral sides in the 3D-dimension. Each cell of the SOM represents a cluster defined by the five parameters employed in the classification. The significant wave height, the wave period and the wave direction are represented by the size, the colour intensity and the direction of the arrow; the pink arrow represents the wind vector. The background of each hexagon has been filled in a blue scale, function of the frequency of occurrence. As it can be seen in the figure, this classification technique is capable of extracting all the possible sea states and the transition between them. The magnitudes of the parameters which define the centroids vary smoothly from one cell to another. The most energetic sea states present W-WNW
directions (i=17, j=14). The higher amount of data is grouped in clusters with low energy sea states (i=6, j=11).&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Figure 2 shows several SOMs for different locations along the northern coast of Spain. In this case, we are considering (Hs, Tp, θ) and a 10x10 SOM. In the presentation, the theoretical basis and some examples will show the ability of this methodology to describe the multidimensional wave climate.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Aplicación de Métodos de Clasificación al Downscaling Estadístico</title><link>https://santandermetgroup.github.io/website-demo/event/2001-aplicacion-de-metodos-de-clasificacion/</link><pubDate>Tue, 20 Nov 2001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://santandermetgroup.github.io/website-demo/event/2001-aplicacion-de-metodos-de-clasificacion/</guid><description>&lt;p>En este artículo se analizan diversas alternativas para la predicción probabilística de meteoros utilizando el método de análogos, y se presentan resultados de validación en la red principal de estaciones del INM en las diversas cuencas peninsulares. En primer lugar se comparan distintas especificaciones (tamaño de la rejilla y rango horario) del vector 4D que define el “estado de la atmósfera” en base a las predicciones de un modelo numérico. Seguidamente, se describe la forma más conveniente de comprimir esta información, eliminando redundancias, utilizando componentes principales. A continuación, se analizan distintas técnicas de clasificación para obtener un conjunto de estados de la atmósfera análogos a uno dado, de entre aquellos disponibles en una base de datos de estados históricos (reanálisis). Finalmente, se muestra la forma de mejorar la resolución de una predicción realizada por el modelo numérico a partir de la estadística de los meteoros locales observados en las fechas correspondientes a los análogos hallados para el estado definido por la predicción.&lt;/p></description></item></channel></rss>