<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>Casanueva, A. | Santander Meteorology Group</title><link>https://santandermetgroup.github.io/website-demo/author/casanueva-a./</link><atom:link href="https://santandermetgroup.github.io/website-demo/author/casanueva-a./index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><description>Casanueva, A.</description><generator>Wowchemy (https://wowchemy.com)</generator><language>en-us</language><image><url>https://santandermetgroup.github.io/website-demo/media/icon_hu58a305e0ce1458c8ebaf599b64640cde_12944_512x512_fill_lanczos_center_3.png</url><title>Casanueva, A.</title><link>https://santandermetgroup.github.io/website-demo/author/casanueva-a./</link></image><item><title>CORDyS | Contribution to the next generation of CORDEX regional climate projections: Dynamical and Statistical approaches</title><link>https://santandermetgroup.github.io/website-demo/project/cordys/</link><pubDate>Fri, 01 Jan 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://santandermetgroup.github.io/website-demo/project/cordys/</guid><description/></item><item><title>Added value of high resolution RCM simulations and comparison with Statistical Downscaling Methods within the EURO-CORDEX framework</title><link>https://santandermetgroup.github.io/website-demo/event/2016-added-value-of-high-resolution/</link><pubDate>Thu, 01 Jan 1970 00:33:36 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://santandermetgroup.github.io/website-demo/event/2016-added-value-of-high-resolution/</guid><description>&lt;p>High resolution Regional Climate Model (RCM) simulations and Statistical Downscaling Methods (SDMs) are important tools to provide the meteorological variables required in climate impact assessments. The present study analyzes two aspects that should be taken into account before using these methods in specific applications. First, we assess the added value of high resolution simulations from a EURO-CORDEX RCM ensemble. Secondly, RCMs are compared with SDMs, in order to show the merits and limitations of both downscaling techniques. Both aspects are assessed in terms of mean and extreme precipitation indices in Spain.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>The EURO-CORDEX initiative provides an appropriate framework for this study, since a common grid is used for all RCMs and the high and low resolution grids match each other at the grid cell boundaries. The ability of the high-resolution RCM simulations (0.11°) to represent observed precipitation is assessed at their skillful scale, by aggregating the 0.11° grid to the 0.44° resolution and evaluating the added value with respect to the low resolution (0.44°) runs. Since RCMs are prone to systematic biases, the added value of the high resolution runs is also analyzed after applying bias correction methods to the RCMs. Gridded observational products are available over the same grids as the RCMs, such as the Spain02 v4 family of EURO-CORDEX-compliant gridded datasets over Spain. Therefore, the evaluation of the RCMs and the development of the SDMs can be carried out on exactly the same grids, and SDMs produce a downscaling output comparable to the RCMs. A set of SDMs (namely analog resampling, weather typing and different versions of Generalized Linear Models) are applied using ERA-Interim predictor variables under a cross-validation approach.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Results show limited evidence for an added value of the high resolution RCM simulations in terms of seasonal mean biases. There is an indication of added value in the spatial patterns; however, this is not statistically significant after bias correcting both simulations.&lt;br />
The comparison of RCMs and SDMs based on specific precipitation-derived indices may not be fair as long as they are related to parameters that have been optimized in the calibration phase of SDMs. When the comparison is performed in terms of non-optimized parameters (e.g. dry spells), both downscaling techniques present similar skills and limitations.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Assessing the role of regional climate models as intermediaries between global models and bias correction methods</title><link>https://santandermetgroup.github.io/website-demo/event/2015-assessing-the-role-of-regional/</link><pubDate>Thu, 01 Jan 1970 00:33:35 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://santandermetgroup.github.io/website-demo/event/2015-assessing-the-role-of-regional/</guid><description>&lt;p>Recently, the amount of publicly available future climate simulations has greatly increased, allowing for more robust climate change uncertainty assessments. However, the number of available experiments is strongly reduced when considering only computationally costly regional climate model (RCM) runs. These simulations are used as input for many impact studies, but usually after a statistical post-processing which takes into account the observations at station level (or very high resolution grids) and is commonly known as bias correction. These methods have been primarily developed for removing model biases, although they are also implicitly used to bridge the scale mismatch between model grids and local observations. &lt;/p>
&lt;p>Given that bias correction can be directly applied to Global Circulation Models (GCMs), we assess the role of RCMs as intermediaries between GCMs and bias correction methods. We apply different bias correction methods (from the simple scaling to different versions of the quantile-quantile mapping) directly to daily precipitation from a set of coarse resolution CMIP5 GCMs and compare them with bias-corrected EURO-CORDEX RCMs (namely COSMO-CLM and RCA at 12km horizontal resolution) for historical and future periods. We use a subset of European stations from the ECA&amp;amp;D dataset as observational reference for the bias correction. Additionally, a refined analysis in the Ebro catchment illustrates the effect of bias correction on spatial climate variability. &lt;/p>
&lt;p>The evaluation experiment of the historical simulations in a cross-validation framework shows that bias corrected RCMs and GCMs typically present similar biases, but an added value of RCMs is found for the spatial analysis. Second, the basic features and the overall magnitude of the climate change signal are preserved after applying bias correction, although in some cases the uncertainty in the climate change signal is amplified by bias correction.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Ability of statistical and dynamical downscaling approaches to reproduce mean and heavy precipitation at different spatial scales over Europe</title><link>https://santandermetgroup.github.io/website-demo/event/2013-ability-of-statistical-and-dynamical/</link><pubDate>Thu, 01 Jan 1970 00:33:33 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://santandermetgroup.github.io/website-demo/event/2013-ability-of-statistical-and-dynamical/</guid><description>&lt;p>The present study compares statistical downscaling methods (SDMs) and dynamical downscaling with nested regional climate models (RCMs) at different target spatial scales over two European regions. All downscaling products were developed in the framework of Euro-CORDEX and use the ERA-Interim reanalysis as boundary conditions (in RCMs) and as large-scale predictor data (in SDMs). Downscaled precipitation is evaluated at two horizontal resolutions (0.11º and 0.44º) using simulations from the Euro-CORDEX RCM ensemble and SDS methods trained against gridded observational data. The objectives of the work are: (1) to compare both downscaling methodologies, to identify their respective strengths and weaknesses at (2) different spatial scales and considering (3) mean and heavy daily precipitation, and (4) to assess the impact of bias correction methods.&lt;br />
We focus on two target areas in Europe: Continental Spain and the European Alps, where high-resolution and high-quality gridded observational data sets are available. Moreover, these areas represent a variety of climate conditions. Over Spain, the Spain011/044 data sets are considered, which exactly match the Euro-CORDEX grid over Spain. The Alpine data set has been derived from the EURO4M gridded precipitation product provided by MeteoSwiss at 5km resolution. Observations were spatially averaged to match the Euro-CORDEX grid cells. In order to make the SDM results comparable, they were calibrated using the gridded observations as predictand and model performance was evaluated in a cross-validation framework. Bias correction methods and an additional SD step are applied to the RCM data to also incorporate observational information. The ability of the high-resolution RCM simulations (0.11°) to represent observed precipitation is furthermore assessed at their skillful scale, by aggregating the 0.11° grid to the 0.44° resolution and evaluating the added value with respect to the low resolution (0.44°) runs.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Assessing Fire Weather Index using statistical downscaling and spatial interpolation techniques in Greece</title><link>https://santandermetgroup.github.io/website-demo/event/2013-assessing-fire-weather-index-using/</link><pubDate>Thu, 01 Jan 1970 00:33:33 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://santandermetgroup.github.io/website-demo/event/2013-assessing-fire-weather-index-using/</guid><description>&lt;p>Forest fires have always been present in the Mediterranean ecosystems, thus they constitute a major ecological&lt;br />
and socio-economic issue. The last few decades though, the number of forest fires has significantly increased, as&lt;br />
well as their severity and impact on the environment. Local fire danger projections are often required when dealing&lt;br />
with wild fire research. In the present study the application of statistical downscaling and spatial interpolation&lt;br />
methods was performed to the Canadian Fire Weather Index (FWI), in order to assess forest fire risk in Greece.&lt;br />
The FWI is used worldwide (including the Mediterranean basin) to estimate the fire danger in a generalized fuel&lt;br />
type, based solely on weather observations. The meteorological inputs to the FWI System are noon values of&lt;br />
dry-bulb temperature, air relative humidity, 10m wind speed and precipitation during the previous 24 hours.&lt;br />
The statistical downscaling methods are based on a statistical model that takes into account empirical relationships&lt;br />
between large scale variables (used as predictors) and local scale variables. In the framework&lt;br />
of the current study the statistical downscaling portal developed by the Santander Meteorology Group&lt;br />
(&lt;a href="https://www.meteo.unican.es/downscaling" title="https://www.meteo.unican.es/downscaling">https://www.meteo.unican.es/downscaling&lt;/a>) in the framework of the EU project CLIMRUN (&lt;a href="http://www.climrun.eu" title="www.climrun.eu">www.climrun.eu&lt;/a>)&lt;br />
was used to downscale non standard parameters related to forest fire risk.&lt;br />
In this study, two different approaches were adopted. Firstly, the analogue downscaling technique was directly&lt;br />
performed to the FWI index values and secondly the same downscaling technique was performed indirectly through&lt;br />
the meteorological inputs of the index. In both cases, the statistical downscaling portal was used considering the&lt;br />
ERA-Interim reanalysis as predictands due to the lack of observations at noon.&lt;br />
Additionally, a three-dimensional (3D) interpolation method of position and elevation, based on Thin Plate Splines&lt;br />
(TPS) was used, to interpolate the ERA-Interim data used to calculate the index. Results from this method were&lt;br />
compared with the statistical downscaling results obtained from the portal.&lt;br />
Finally, FWI was computed using weather observations obtained from the Hellenic National Meteorological Service,&lt;br />
mainly in the south continental part of Greece and a comparison with the previous results was performed.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>A multi-physics ensemble over the CORDEX-Africa domain</title><link>https://santandermetgroup.github.io/website-demo/event/2012-a-multi-physics-ensemble-over-the/</link><pubDate>Thu, 01 Jan 1970 00:33:32 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://santandermetgroup.github.io/website-demo/event/2012-a-multi-physics-ensemble-over-the/</guid><description>&lt;p>WRF (Weather Research and Forecasting) model is a state of the art regional model whose use has spread worldwide. This kind of models solves the atmospheric circulation equations for a resolution higher than the Global Circulation Models (GCMs). Due to the coarse resolution of the latter, Regional Climate Models (RCMs) as WRF try to better represent climate for specific regions. WRF is a very flexible model and several different configurations can be selected changing the different parameterizations. For this reason, each configuration can be considered as a different model and the biases of the different configurations are as large as those corresponding to different RCMs (Vautard et al. 2012). Nowadays many research groups have run their own configurations, but analysing the sensitivity of the model to each configuration for each region is a relevant issue, since results can change significantly.&lt;br />
We focus our analysis on the African domain, which is the CORDEX priority. Our study is motivated by the need to find the best set of parameterizations for Africa concerning temperature and precipitation.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Assessment of extreme temperature percentiles by means of Regional Climate Models</title><link>https://santandermetgroup.github.io/website-demo/event/2012-assessment-of-extreme-temperature-percentiles/</link><pubDate>Thu, 01 Jan 1970 00:33:32 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://santandermetgroup.github.io/website-demo/event/2012-assessment-of-extreme-temperature-percentiles/</guid><description>&lt;p>The study of extreme events has become of great interest in the recent years due to their direct impact on society. Extremes can be evaluated both by using extreme value theory or deriving extreme indicators, which are usually based on statistics on the tail of the probability distribution. Some of the most commonly used indicators are based on percentiles. In this study we calculate the most extreme percentiles in maximum (90p, 95p and 99p) and minimum (1p, 5p and 10p) temperature derived from the application of dynamical downscaling methods in the Iberian Peninsula. We analyze the regional climate models (RCMs) of the ENSEMBLES (EU-funded) and ESCENA (strategic action of Plan Nacional de I+D+i 2008-2011 funded by the Spanish government) projects.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>The dynamical downscaling methods are first tested in present climate with quasi-perfect (reanalysis) boundary conditions in order to know to what extent these approaches properly reproduce the observed percentiles. Then, we analyze the effect of nesting the RCMs to different Global Circulation Models (GCMs) on the 20C3M scenario. The study focuses on the end of the 20th century (1961–2000), used as a reference period, and assesses the changes projected for the period 2031–2050 considering the A1B emission scenario.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>The comparison among the different models is obtained in terms of both the annual and seasonal biases. Analyzing the bias patterns, we are able to know whether the inter-RCM variability leads to larger biases than those due to the driving GCM. Moreover, due to the sensitivity of the results to the observational dataset used for the comparison, we consider the new, public, gridded dataset developed for continental Spain and Balearic Islands with 0.2º resolution (Spain02; Herrera et al. 2012).&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Herrera, S., Gutierrez, J., Ancell, R., Pons, M., Frias, M., and Fernandez, J.: Development and Analysis of a 50 year high-resolution daily gridded precipitation dataset over Spain (Spain02). International Journal of Climatology 32:74-85 DOI: 10.1002/joc.2256 .&lt;/p></description></item></channel></rss>