<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>L. Fita | Santander Meteorology Group</title><link>https://santandermetgroup.github.io/website-demo/author/l.-fita/</link><atom:link href="https://santandermetgroup.github.io/website-demo/author/l.-fita/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><description>L. Fita</description><generator>Wowchemy (https://wowchemy.com)</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Thu, 01 Jan 2015 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><image><url>https://santandermetgroup.github.io/website-demo/media/icon_hu58a305e0ce1458c8ebaf599b64640cde_12944_512x512_fill_lanczos_center_3.png</url><title>L. Fita</title><link>https://santandermetgroup.github.io/website-demo/author/l.-fita/</link></image><item><title>A set of regional climate change scenarios over Spain: ESCENA Project</title><link>https://santandermetgroup.github.io/website-demo/event/2015-a-set-of-regional-climate/</link><pubDate>Thu, 01 Jan 2015 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://santandermetgroup.github.io/website-demo/event/2015-a-set-of-regional-climate/</guid><description>&lt;p>ESCENA (&lt;a href="http://proyectoescena.uclm.es" title="http://proyectoescena.uclm.es">http://proyectoescena.uclm.es&lt;/a>) was part of the Spanish Strategic action on energy and&lt;br />
climate change. Funded by the Spanish government, this call aimed at providing the scientific basis&lt;br />
for the assessment of regional climate change impacts over Spain (including continental Spain, the&lt;br />
Balearic and Canary islands). The ESCENA project (2008-2011) agglutinated the regional climate&lt;br />
modelling efforts. Four different institutions contributed simulations using 4 different Regional Climate&lt;br />
Models (RCMs): Universidad de Castilla-La Mancha (UCLM, PROMES model), Universidad de&lt;br />
Murcia (UMUR, MM5 model), Universidad de Alcalá de Henares (UAHE, REMO model) and&lt;br />
Universidad de Cantabria (UCAN, WRF model).&lt;br />
The boundary forcing came from the Global Climate Model (GCM) simulations generated by the third&lt;br />
Coupled Model Intercomparison Project (CMIP3) for the 4th IPCC Assessment Report (AR4). We&lt;br />
used three different GCMs (ECHAM5-MPIOM, CNRM-CM3 and HadCM3) forced by the A1B, A2, and&lt;br />
B1 emissions scenarios. An interesting feature of the experimental setup in ESCENA was the&lt;br />
GCM/RCM matrix, which was designed to enable the comparison of different RCMs projections with a&lt;br />
single specific change (RCM, scenario, GCM, parameterization). This allows the exploration of the&lt;br />
role of different sources of uncertainty. The RCM simulations cover a common minimum domain&lt;br />
encompassing the whole Spanish territory with a horizontal resolution of 25 Km.&lt;br />
The project focused on the near future, simulating a control period (1950-2000, 1950 left as spin-up&lt;br />
and disregarded in the analyses) forced by the 20C3M historical scenario and continued by a 50-year&lt;br />
period, 2001-2050, of future projection. In this work we present the main results of the project,&lt;br />
focusing on the future climate projection scenarios for impact-relevant variables.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>A methodology to evaluate regional-scale offshore wind energy resources.</title><link>https://santandermetgroup.github.io/website-demo/event/2011-a-methodology-to-evaluate-regional-scale/</link><pubDate>Sat, 01 Jan 2011 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://santandermetgroup.github.io/website-demo/event/2011-a-methodology-to-evaluate-regional-scale/</guid><description>&lt;p>The economic viability of offshore wind farms depends on the favorable wind conditions. It is, however, a challenge to study winds in the marine atmospheric environment. A common problem is the data collection since the wind dataset requires enough spatial and temporal resolution. Numerical hindcast (reanalysis) constitutes an alternative to disperse instrumental observations although two considerations should be studied in the reanalysis for regional purposes: the domain and the spatial resolution and a validation-calibration procedure using instrumental data. Accordingly, the wind resource process can be described by the following cascade activities: the coarse spatial wind fields from global meteorological experiments; the regional winds from a dynamic downscaling coupled to the global reanalysis fields; the validation and calibration procedures by using instrumental observations; and, finally, the characterization of winds for evaluation of the wind resource. This work proposes a methodology to study wind energy resources in a regional offshore area and shows the application along the offshore Spanish coast.&lt;/p></description></item></channel></rss>