<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>Temperature | Santander Meteorology Group</title><link>https://santandermetgroup.github.io/website-demo/tag/temperature/</link><atom:link href="https://santandermetgroup.github.io/website-demo/tag/temperature/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><description>Temperature</description><generator>Wowchemy (https://wowchemy.com)</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Tue, 25 Sep 2012 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><image><url>https://santandermetgroup.github.io/website-demo/media/icon_hu58a305e0ce1458c8ebaf599b64640cde_12944_512x512_fill_lanczos_center_3.png</url><title>Temperature</title><link>https://santandermetgroup.github.io/website-demo/tag/temperature/</link></image><item><title>A critical reassessment of statistical downscaling techniques under climate change conditions in Spain: Accuracy, distributional similarity and robustness</title><link>https://santandermetgroup.github.io/website-demo/event/2012-a-critical-reassessment-of-statistical/</link><pubDate>Tue, 25 Sep 2012 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://santandermetgroup.github.io/website-demo/event/2012-a-critical-reassessment-of-statistical/</guid><description>&lt;p>The performance of a wide range of statistical methods to downscale temperature (both maxima and minima) and precipitation in Spain is critically reassessed with respect to their robust applicability in climate change studies. For such purpose, we cross-validate the different techniques focusing on three distinct aspects: 1) accuracy (correlation, etc.), 2) distributional similarity (KS and PDF scores), and 3) stationarity/robustness under climate change conditions. For the latter, which is normally missed in state-of-the-art downscaling studies, we consider anomalous warm/cold (temperature) and dry/wet (precipitation) periods from the observational records - which serve as surrogates of possible future climate alterations - and test the performance of the methods, as compared to random periods. It is found that a near-perfect association between observed and downscaled series (e.g. high correlations) may hide important shortcomings in terms of distributional similarity and robustness. Therefore, a wide collection of downscaling configurations (domain-predictor-methodology) are evaluated in order to identify those being the most appropriate to deal with this issue.
This study is part of the work done in the project ESTCENA, a strategic action of Plan Nacional de I+D+i 2008-2011.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Assessment of extreme temperature percentiles by means of Regional Climate Models</title><link>https://santandermetgroup.github.io/website-demo/event/2012-assessment-of-extreme-temperature-percentiles/</link><pubDate>Mon, 07 May 2012 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://santandermetgroup.github.io/website-demo/event/2012-assessment-of-extreme-temperature-percentiles/</guid><description>&lt;p>The study of extreme events has become of great interest in the recent years due to their direct impact on society. Extremes can be evaluated both by using extreme value theory or deriving extreme indicators, which are usually based on statistics on the tail of the probability distribution. Some of the most commonly used indicators are based on percentiles. In this study we calculate the most extreme percentiles in maximum (90p, 95p and 99p) and minimum (1p, 5p and 10p) temperature derived from the application of dynamical downscaling methods in the Iberian Peninsula. We analyze the regional climate models (RCMs) of the ENSEMBLES (EU-funded) and ESCENA (strategic action of Plan Nacional de I+D+i 2008-2011 funded by the Spanish government) projects.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>The dynamical downscaling methods are first tested in present climate with quasi-perfect (reanalysis) boundary conditions in order to know to what extent these approaches properly reproduce the observed percentiles. Then, we analyze the effect of nesting the RCMs to different Global Circulation Models (GCMs) on the 20C3M scenario. The study focuses on the end of the 20th century (1961–2000), used as a reference period, and assesses the changes projected for the period 2031–2050 considering the A1B emission scenario.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>The comparison among the different models is obtained in terms of both the annual and seasonal biases. Analyzing the bias patterns, we are able to know whether the inter-RCM variability leads to larger biases than those due to the driving GCM. Moreover, due to the sensitivity of the results to the observational dataset used for the comparison, we consider the new, public, gridded dataset developed for continental Spain and Balearic Islands with 0.2º resolution (Spain02; Herrera et al. 2012).&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Herrera, S., Gutierrez, J., Ancell, R., Pons, M., Frias, M., and Fernandez, J.: Development and Analysis of a 50 year high-resolution daily gridded precipitation dataset over Spain (Spain02). International Journal of Climatology 32:74-85 DOI: 10.1002/joc.2256 .&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Actual and future trends of extreme values of temperature for the NW Iberian Peninsula</title><link>https://santandermetgroup.github.io/website-demo/event/2009-actual-and-future-trends-of/</link><pubDate>Mon, 28 Sep 2009 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://santandermetgroup.github.io/website-demo/event/2009-actual-and-future-trends-of/</guid><description>&lt;p>It is now very well established that yearly averaged temperatures are increasing due to anthropogenic climate change. In the area of Galicia (NW Spain) this trend has also been determined. The main objective of this work is to assess actual and future trends of different extreme indices of temperature, which are of crucial importance for many impact studies.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>As direct GCM-output significantly underestimates the variance of daily surface temperature variables in NW Spain, these are obtained by applying a statistical downscaling technique (analog method), using 850hPa temperature and mean sea level pressure as combined predictors. The predictor fields have been extracted from a multi-model multi initial conditions ensemble of 14 runs of three GCMs participating in the IPCC AR4.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>For 1960-2006 results show a significant increase of the number of days with maximum temperatures above the 90th percentile. Furthermore, a significant decrease of the days with maximum temperatures below the 10th percentile has been found. The tendencies of minimum temperatures are reverse: less nights with minimum temperatures below the 10th percentile and more with minimum temperatures above 90th percentile. Those tendencies can be observed all over the year, but are more pronounced in summer. Results for relationship between the above mentioned extreme values and different North Atlantic teleconnection patterns show that local tendencies are associated with trends of EA (Eastern Atlantic) and SCA (Scandinavian) patterns. The NAO (North Atlantic Oscillation) only in winter is related to the number of cold days.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>The ensemble climate projections generated with the analog method indicate that the observed (linear) trends of maximum and minimum temperatures in NW Spain are expected to continue in the next decades. Furthermore the uncertainty interval of these projections (2021-2050) is dominated by model uncertainties rather than by forcing uncertainties.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>We conclude that more frequent hot days as well as an increasing probability of summertime heat waves are to be expected in the next decades. Cold days tend to diminish, decreasing the probability of wintertime cold waves and leaving a greater part of the area under study without frost throughout the year.&lt;/p></description></item></channel></rss>