<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>Dynamical downscaling | Santander Meteorology Group</title><link>https://santandermetgroup.github.io/website-demo/tag/dynamical-downscaling/</link><atom:link href="https://santandermetgroup.github.io/website-demo/tag/dynamical-downscaling/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><description>Dynamical downscaling</description><generator>Wowchemy (https://wowchemy.com)</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Thu, 01 Jan 1970 00:33:35 +0000</lastBuildDate><image><url>https://santandermetgroup.github.io/website-demo/media/icon_hu58a305e0ce1458c8ebaf599b64640cde_12944_512x512_fill_lanczos_center_3.png</url><title>Dynamical downscaling</title><link>https://santandermetgroup.github.io/website-demo/tag/dynamical-downscaling/</link></image><item><title>A set of regional climate change scenarios over Spain: ESCENA Project</title><link>https://santandermetgroup.github.io/website-demo/event/a-set-of-regional-climate/</link><pubDate>Thu, 01 Jan 1970 00:33:35 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://santandermetgroup.github.io/website-demo/event/a-set-of-regional-climate/</guid><description>&lt;p>ESCENA (&lt;a href="http://proyectoescena.uclm.es" title="http://proyectoescena.uclm.es">http://proyectoescena.uclm.es&lt;/a>) was part of the Spanish Strategic action on energy and&lt;br />
climate change. Funded by the Spanish government, this call aimed at providing the scientific basis&lt;br />
for the assessment of regional climate change impacts over Spain (including continental Spain, the&lt;br />
Balearic and Canary islands). The ESCENA project (2008-2011) agglutinated the regional climate&lt;br />
modelling efforts. Four different institutions contributed simulations using 4 different Regional Climate&lt;br />
Models (RCMs): Universidad de Castilla-La Mancha (UCLM, PROMES model), Universidad de&lt;br />
Murcia (UMUR, MM5 model), Universidad de Alcalá de Henares (UAHE, REMO model) and&lt;br />
Universidad de Cantabria (UCAN, WRF model).&lt;br />
The boundary forcing came from the Global Climate Model (GCM) simulations generated by the third&lt;br />
Coupled Model Intercomparison Project (CMIP3) for the 4th IPCC Assessment Report (AR4). We&lt;br />
used three different GCMs (ECHAM5-MPIOM, CNRM-CM3 and HadCM3) forced by the A1B, A2, and&lt;br />
B1 emissions scenarios. An interesting feature of the experimental setup in ESCENA was the&lt;br />
GCM/RCM matrix, which was designed to enable the comparison of different RCMs projections with a&lt;br />
single specific change (RCM, scenario, GCM, parameterization). This allows the exploration of the&lt;br />
role of different sources of uncertainty. The RCM simulations cover a common minimum domain&lt;br />
encompassing the whole Spanish territory with a horizontal resolution of 25 Km.&lt;br />
The project focused on the near future, simulating a control period (1950-2000, 1950 left as spin-up&lt;br />
and disregarded in the analyses) forced by the 20C3M historical scenario and continued by a 50-year&lt;br />
period, 2001-2050, of future projection. In this work we present the main results of the project,&lt;br />
focusing on the future climate projection scenarios for impact-relevant variables.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Activities of the Santander MetGroup in relation to M5S, GCM, RCM, ESD and OBS</title><link>https://santandermetgroup.github.io/website-demo/event/activities-of-the-santander-metgroup/</link><pubDate>Thu, 01 Jan 1970 00:33:34 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://santandermetgroup.github.io/website-demo/event/activities-of-the-santander-metgroup/</guid><description>&lt;p>Summary of the Santander MetGroup activity, as hosting group of the workshop.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>A Comparison of Statistical, Dynamical and Combined MOS Downscaling Approaches in the Framework of the PNACC-2012 Spanish Program</title><link>https://santandermetgroup.github.io/website-demo/event/a-comparison-of-statistical-dynamical/</link><pubDate>Thu, 01 Jan 1970 00:33:33 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://santandermetgroup.github.io/website-demo/event/a-comparison-of-statistical-dynamical/</guid><description>&lt;p>In this work we present a comparison of dynamical and statistical (both perfect prognosis and Model Output Statistics, MOS) downscaling techniques focusing on maximum temperature and precipitation in the Iberian peninsula —a complex climate region with Atlantic, continental, and Mediterranean influences.— To this aim, the same forcing conditions (from ERA40 re- analysis data) are considered for all methods and a k- fold cross validation is conducted focusing on different validation scores. The methods are assessed not only in terms of accuracy and distributional similarity, but also considering their robustness/stationarity in changing climate conditions; to this aim, anomalous historical periods (warm/cold for maximum temperature and wet/dry for precipitation) are used as surrogates of possible future climate alterations, and differences with normal periods are tested using a standard Student t-test. As a result, the strengths and limitations of these techniques in terms of their robust applicability in climate change studies are reported.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>As most important results, the statistical/dynamical downscaling approaches show the best/worst performance in terms of accuracy and distributional similarity; however, MOS techniques are able to correct the deficiencies of the dynamical models according to the referece observations. However, the known limitations of the analogue method to reach unobserved values affect the robustness of statistical downscaling methods, mainly in the case of the maximum temperature, which are less robust than the dynamical ones.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Finally, we compare the 21st century regional projections for Spain obtained with the above methods in the framework of the Spanish Plan for Regional Climate Change Scenarios (PNACC-2012) showing that, when discarding nonrobust methods, both dynamical and statistical projections are in good agreement.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Assessment of extreme temperature percentiles by means of Regional Climate Models</title><link>https://santandermetgroup.github.io/website-demo/event/assessment-of-extreme-temperature-percentiles/</link><pubDate>Thu, 01 Jan 1970 00:33:32 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://santandermetgroup.github.io/website-demo/event/assessment-of-extreme-temperature-percentiles/</guid><description>&lt;p>The study of extreme events has become of great interest in the recent years due to their direct impact on society. Extremes can be evaluated both by using extreme value theory or deriving extreme indicators, which are usually based on statistics on the tail of the probability distribution. Some of the most commonly used indicators are based on percentiles. In this study we calculate the most extreme percentiles in maximum (90p, 95p and 99p) and minimum (1p, 5p and 10p) temperature derived from the application of dynamical downscaling methods in the Iberian Peninsula. We analyze the regional climate models (RCMs) of the ENSEMBLES (EU-funded) and ESCENA (strategic action of Plan Nacional de I+D+i 2008-2011 funded by the Spanish government) projects.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>The dynamical downscaling methods are first tested in present climate with quasi-perfect (reanalysis) boundary conditions in order to know to what extent these approaches properly reproduce the observed percentiles. Then, we analyze the effect of nesting the RCMs to different Global Circulation Models (GCMs) on the 20C3M scenario. The study focuses on the end of the 20th century (1961–2000), used as a reference period, and assesses the changes projected for the period 2031–2050 considering the A1B emission scenario.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>The comparison among the different models is obtained in terms of both the annual and seasonal biases. Analyzing the bias patterns, we are able to know whether the inter-RCM variability leads to larger biases than those due to the driving GCM. Moreover, due to the sensitivity of the results to the observational dataset used for the comparison, we consider the new, public, gridded dataset developed for continental Spain and Balearic Islands with 0.2º resolution (Spain02; Herrera et al. 2012).&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Herrera, S., Gutierrez, J., Ancell, R., Pons, M., Frias, M., and Fernandez, J.: Development and Analysis of a 50 year high-resolution daily gridded precipitation dataset over Spain (Spain02). International Journal of Climatology 32:74-85 DOI: 10.1002/joc.2256 .&lt;/p></description></item></channel></rss>