<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>ETH Zurich | Santander Meteorology Group</title><link>https://santandermetgroup.github.io/website-demo/collab_institutions/eth-zurich/</link><atom:link href="https://santandermetgroup.github.io/website-demo/collab_institutions/eth-zurich/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><description>ETH Zurich</description><generator>Wowchemy (https://wowchemy.com)</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Wed, 11 Mar 2015 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><image><url>https://santandermetgroup.github.io/website-demo/media/icon_hu58a305e0ce1458c8ebaf599b64640cde_12944_512x512_fill_lanczos_center_3.png</url><title>ETH Zurich</title><link>https://santandermetgroup.github.io/website-demo/collab_institutions/eth-zurich/</link></image><item><title>Assessing the role of regional climate models as intermediaries between global models and bias correction methods</title><link>https://santandermetgroup.github.io/website-demo/event/2015-assessing-the-role-of-regional/</link><pubDate>Wed, 11 Mar 2015 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://santandermetgroup.github.io/website-demo/event/2015-assessing-the-role-of-regional/</guid><description>&lt;p>Recently, the amount of publicly available future climate simulations has greatly increased, allowing for more robust climate change uncertainty assessments. However, the number of available experiments is strongly reduced when considering only computationally costly regional climate model (RCM) runs. These simulations are used as input for many impact studies, but usually after a statistical post-processing which takes into account the observations at station level (or very high resolution grids) and is commonly known as bias correction. These methods have been primarily developed for removing model biases, although they are also implicitly used to bridge the scale mismatch between model grids and local observations.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Given that bias correction can be directly applied to Global Circulation Models (GCMs), we assess the role of RCMs as intermediaries between GCMs and bias correction methods. We apply different bias correction methods (from the simple scaling to different versions of the quantile-quantile mapping) directly to daily precipitation from a set of coarse resolution CMIP5 GCMs and compare them with bias-corrected EURO-CORDEX RCMs (namely COSMO-CLM and RCA at 12km horizontal resolution) for historical and future periods. We use a subset of European stations from the ECA&amp;amp;D dataset as observational reference for the bias correction. Additionally, a refined analysis in the Ebro catchment illustrates the effect of bias correction on spatial climate variability.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>The evaluation experiment of the historical simulations in a cross-validation framework shows that bias corrected RCMs and GCMs typically present similar biases, but an added value of RCMs is found for the spatial analysis. Second, the basic features and the overall magnitude of the climate change signal are preserved after applying bias correction, although in some cases the uncertainty in the climate change signal is amplified by bias correction.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Ability of statistical and dynamical downscaling approaches to reproduce mean and heavy precipitation at different spatial scales over Europe</title><link>https://santandermetgroup.github.io/website-demo/event/2013-ability-of-statistical-and-dynamical/</link><pubDate>Mon, 04 Nov 2013 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://santandermetgroup.github.io/website-demo/event/2013-ability-of-statistical-and-dynamical/</guid><description>&lt;p>The present study compares statistical downscaling methods (SDMs) and dynamical downscaling with nested regional climate models (RCMs) at different target spatial scales over two European regions. All downscaling products were developed in the framework of Euro-CORDEX and use the ERA-Interim reanalysis as boundary conditions (in RCMs) and as large-scale predictor data (in SDMs). Downscaled precipitation is evaluated at two horizontal resolutions (0.11º and 0.44º) using simulations from the Euro-CORDEX RCM ensemble and SDS methods trained against gridded observational data. The objectives of the work are: (1) to compare both downscaling methodologies, to identify their respective strengths and weaknesses at (2) different spatial scales and considering (3) mean and heavy daily precipitation, and (4) to assess the impact of bias correction methods.
We focus on two target areas in Europe: Continental Spain and the European Alps, where high-resolution and high-quality gridded observational data sets are available. Moreover, these areas represent a variety of climate conditions. Over Spain, the Spain011/044 data sets are considered, which exactly match the Euro-CORDEX grid over Spain. The Alpine data set has been derived from the EURO4M gridded precipitation product provided by MeteoSwiss at 5km resolution. Observations were spatially averaged to match the Euro-CORDEX grid cells. In order to make the SDM results comparable, they were calibrated using the gridded observations as predictand and model performance was evaluated in a cross-validation framework. Bias correction methods and an additional SD step are applied to the RCM data to also incorporate observational information. The ability of the high-resolution RCM simulations (0.11°) to represent observed precipitation is furthermore assessed at their skillful scale, by aggregating the 0.11° grid to the 0.44° resolution and evaluating the added value with respect to the low resolution (0.44°) runs.&lt;/p></description></item></channel></rss>