<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>antonio-s-cofino | Santander Meteorology Group</title><link>https://santandermetgroup.github.io/website-demo/author/antonio-s-cofino/</link><atom:link href="https://santandermetgroup.github.io/website-demo/author/antonio-s-cofino/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><description>antonio-s-cofino</description><generator>Wowchemy (https://wowchemy.com)</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Fri, 01 Jan 2021 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><image><url>https://santandermetgroup.github.io/website-demo/media/icon_hu58a305e0ce1458c8ebaf599b64640cde_12944_512x512_fill_lanczos_center_3.png</url><title>antonio-s-cofino</title><link>https://santandermetgroup.github.io/website-demo/author/antonio-s-cofino/</link></image><item><title>CORDyS | Contribution to the next generation of CORDEX regional climate projections: Dynamical and Statistical approaches</title><link>https://santandermetgroup.github.io/website-demo/project/cordys/</link><pubDate>Fri, 01 Jan 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://santandermetgroup.github.io/website-demo/project/cordys/</guid><description>&lt;p>The Coordinated Regional Climate Downscaling Experiment (CORDEX) initiative has been, for over a decade, the key international coordinating body in the production, scientific analysis and application of future climate projections at regional scale. This unfunded initiative provides a common framework for downscaling activities around the world. The ongoing second phase, focused on regional challenges through Flagship Pilot Studies (FPS) and the production of homogeneous information across the world (CORDEX-CORE), provides key regional climate information and science to the 6th Assessment Report of the Intergovernmental Panel on Climate Change (IPCC).&lt;/p>
&lt;p>The research team of this proposal has been involved in CORDEX activities since its inception. With the support of the Spanish National R&amp;amp;D Programme, we have contributed to CORDEX using dynamical downscaling through Regional Climate Models (RCMs; CORWES 2011-2014 and INSIGNIA 2017-2020) and statistical downscaling, including bias adjustment methods (MULTI-SDM 2016-2019). In this series of projects, we have developed downscaling tools, applied them in the different CORDEX phases, and actively participated in the coordinated science derived from them. This past activity has positioned the team as the only Spanish research group contributing future regional climate projections (European and South American domains at 0.44º) to the CORDEX ensemble, and the first to deploy in Spain a data node of the Earth System Grid Federation (ESGF), in charge of distributing CORDEX data, among others.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>CORDEX is currently facing the downscaling of CMIP6 global climate models (GCMs), which represent the latest generation of Coupled Earth System Models. The CORDyS project aims to contribute to this next generation of CORDEX regional climate projections using both dynamical and statistical downscaling methods, including statistical emulators of the dynamical models. Our objective is to contribute to (1) the process-based evaluation of the driving GCMs, (2) the downscaling of future climate projections for the current standard continental-scale CORDEX EUR-11 domain, (3) the further downscaling of future projections at very high resolution using a convection-permitting RCM and statistical emulators, (4) the distillation of actionable regional climate information for impacts assessment from these new-generation sources, and (5) the dissemination and publication of results and data products in the CORDEX community and ESGF infrastructure.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>These activities build on well-established previous efforts and contribute to the current forefront of CORDEX, positioning the group internationally and contributing to an initiative which returns climate information for, essentially, all projects and research groups working on regional climate research and other users assessing vulnerability, impacts and adaptation measures for future climate change at regional scales. At a national level, the results of this project will inform and contribute to Escenarios-PNACC (Plan Nacional de Adaptación al Cambio Climático), providing climate projections which build on the CORDEX experience and use the reference observational datasets.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Aggregation of Grid and HPC resources for running huge experiments in climate and weather prediction</title><link>https://santandermetgroup.github.io/website-demo/event/2011-aggregation-of-grid-and-hpc/</link><pubDate>Sat, 01 Jan 2011 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://santandermetgroup.github.io/website-demo/event/2011-aggregation-of-grid-and-hpc/</guid><description>&lt;p>The explosion of computer power during the last two decades has increased the number and types of computational resources a researcher has access to. The heterogeneity of architectures and systems along with the different configuration schemas has led to a situation where users find very complicated taking advantage of all the resources available.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>In order to solve this problem, a new computing paradigm called “Grid Computing” appeared as an alternative for flexible access to heterogeneous and geographically distributed computing resources. Typically, creating a Grid infrastructure requires coordination among cluster administrators and the installation of a middleware to unify the access to them. &lt;/p>
&lt;p>Nowadays, users have access to some resources, like HPC infrastructures, which are not shared using any Grid middleware. Under this situation, the user has to manage separately the access to each non-Grid infrastructure, which is quite cumbersome.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>The challenge of this work is to unify the access to Grid and non-Grid resources, allowing researchers to perform huge experiments making use of all the available resources. To achieve this goal, common LRMs used in HPC infrastructures: PBS/Torque, SGE and SLURM and Grid middleware: gLite, GT2.4 and GT4/5 has been considered.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Although nowadays there are several Grid meta-schedulers, none of them has the capabilities needed. To solve the problem of unified access to Grid and non-Grid resources, the GridWay meta-scheduler and his plugin oriented architecture has been used.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Moreover, as Gridway doesn’t provide access to non Grid resources, new GridWay plugins which grant access to non-Grid resources (PBS/Torque, SGE and SLURM) have been developed. These plugins are based on the raw access to clusters provided to the users; typically a ssh account and LRM’s CLI.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>As an application of this tool it has been integrated into the WRF4G framework. WRF is high demanding application of HPC resources. WRF4G is a framework that allows the management of the execution of huge experiments, consisting in thousands of jobs (HTC). With this tool we are providing a homogeneous access to Grid and non-Grid resources to the WRF4G users. &lt;/p>
&lt;p>The Earth Sciences community, in particular Climate &amp;amp; Weather community, is high demanding HPC user community, therefore it will benefit from this unification of Grid and non-Grid resources.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>A cloud-computing system on the grid through virtualization</title><link>https://santandermetgroup.github.io/website-demo/event/2009-a-cloud-computing-system-on-the/</link><pubDate>Thu, 01 Jan 2009 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://santandermetgroup.github.io/website-demo/event/2009-a-cloud-computing-system-on-the/</guid><description>&lt;p>Nowadays, scientists who make use of the grid are experiencing incompatibility problems between the scientific application that is executed on Working Nodes (WN) and the software installed on them; such as operating system, libraries, and grid middleware. On the other hand, scientists have problems to submit their jobs to different grid sites, because of the grid does not provide a software installation standard on them. This work presents the integration of virtualization technology on grid WN's. This way, users can introduce an application into a virtual machine (VM) with different software to the one installed on the WN. Thus, the job submitted by the user, will cause the VM to start on a WN of some site and to automatically execute a scientific application that may have been previously prepared in a user friendly environment. This work, which is based on the cloud computing notion, lets the users to execute applications on the grid, in isolation from lower software layers. Results have achieved the expected objective: to let users submit scientific applications to the grid, isolating application dependences from the grid software environment.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Analysing the multidimensional wave climate with self organizing maps</title><link>https://santandermetgroup.github.io/website-demo/event/2009-analysing-the-multidimensional-wave-climate/</link><pubDate>Thu, 01 Jan 2009 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://santandermetgroup.github.io/website-demo/event/2009-analysing-the-multidimensional-wave-climate/</guid><description>&lt;p>The term “wave climate” usually refers to the statistical distribution of several oceanographical geophysical variables. Components of the wave climate are variables such as wind velocity, W, wind direction, θW, significant wave height, Hs, peak period, Tp, and mean wave direction, θ. Usually, the classical analysis of the long-term distribution of wave climate is addressed using just one variable (f.i., long-term distribution of significant wave height) or at most bidimensionally (f.i., the bidimensional distribution of Hs and Tp). It is clear that the joint probability distribution of these five variables (Hs, Tp, θ, W, θW) is not easy to able to cope with. However, this problem is solved applying a non-linear clustering algorithm, namely the Self Organizing Maps (SOM), a neural network technique capable of classifying the high dimensional input reanalysis data in a low number of centroids (clusters) in an ordered sheet shape representation (Camus et al, 2007). The neurons are connected to adjacent elements by a neighbourhood relation. A multidimensional histogram of the sea state parameters is obtained allowing an easy further treatment of the classified sea states. &lt;/p>
&lt;p>Figure 1 shows a 23x23 SOM applied to a particular site located in Villano, Galicia (Spain). In this case, the original data space has been projected into a toroid lattice being the data accommodated in a circular way. This toroid shape has been again projected into the plane for a better visualization, separating the centroids which are located together, the centroids located in the upper side of the sheet are joined with the centroids&lt;br />
located on the lower side of the sheet and with the lateral sides in the 3D-dimension. Each cell of the SOM represents a cluster defined by the five parameters employed in the classification. The significant wave height, the wave period and the wave direction are represented by the size, the colour intensity and the direction of the arrow; the pink arrow represents the wind vector. The background of each hexagon has been filled in a blue scale, function of the frequency of occurrence. As it can be seen in the figure, this classification technique is capable of extracting all the possible sea states and the transition between them. The magnitudes of the parameters which define the centroids vary smoothly from one cell to another. The most energetic sea states present W-WNW&lt;br />
directions (i=17, j=14). The higher amount of data is grouped in clusters with low energy sea states (i=6, j=11). &lt;/p>
&lt;p>Figure 2 shows several SOMs for different locations along the northern coast of Spain. In this case, we are considering (Hs, Tp, θ) and a 10x10 SOM. In the presentation, the theoretical basis and some examples will show the ability of this methodology to describe the multidimensional wave climate.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Aplicaciones en Ciencias de la Tierra: vo.meteo.es-ngi.eu</title><link>https://santandermetgroup.github.io/website-demo/event/2009-aplicaciones-en-ciencias-de-la/</link><pubDate>Thu, 01 Jan 2009 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://santandermetgroup.github.io/website-demo/event/2009-aplicaciones-en-ciencias-de-la/</guid><description>&lt;p>Revisón de la situación actual del Área de Aplicaciones, concretamente Ciencias de a Tierra, en la Red Española de eCiencia. En esta presentación se repasa las actividades realizadas durante el último año de las aplicaciones y pilotos desplegadas en la Red, y concretamene la creación de la VO vo.meteo.es-ngi.eu.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Aplicación de Métodos de Clasificación al Downscaling Estadístico</title><link>https://santandermetgroup.github.io/website-demo/event/2001-aplicacion-de-metodos-de-clasificacion/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 2001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://santandermetgroup.github.io/website-demo/event/2001-aplicacion-de-metodos-de-clasificacion/</guid><description>&lt;p>En este artículo se analizan diversas alternativas para la predicción probabilística de meteoros utilizando el método de análogos, y se presentan resultados de validación en la red principal de estaciones del INM en las diversas cuencas peninsulares. En primer lugar se comparan distintas especificaciones (tamaño de la rejilla y rango horario) del vector 4D que define el “estado de la atmósfera” en base a las predicciones de un modelo numérico. Seguidamente, se describe la forma más conveniente de comprimir esta información, eliminando redundancias, utilizando componentes principales. A continuación, se analizan distintas técnicas de clasificación para obtener un conjunto de estados de la atmósfera análogos a uno dado, de entre aquellos disponibles en una base de datos de estados históricos (reanálisis). Finalmente, se muestra la forma de mejorar la resolución de una predicción realizada por el modelo numérico a partir de la estadística de los meteoros locales observados en las fechas correspondientes a los análogos hallados para el estado definido por la predicción.&lt;/p></description></item></channel></rss>