<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>C. Giannakopoulos | Santander Meteorology Group</title><link>https://santandermetgroup.github.io/website-demo/author/c.-giannakopoulos/</link><atom:link href="https://santandermetgroup.github.io/website-demo/author/c.-giannakopoulos/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><description>C. Giannakopoulos</description><generator>Wowchemy (https://wowchemy.com)</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Tue, 01 Jan 2013 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><image><url>https://santandermetgroup.github.io/website-demo/media/icon_hu58a305e0ce1458c8ebaf599b64640cde_12944_512x512_fill_lanczos_center_3.png</url><title>C. Giannakopoulos</title><link>https://santandermetgroup.github.io/website-demo/author/c.-giannakopoulos/</link></image><item><title>Assessing Fire Weather Index using statistical downscaling and spatial interpolation techniques in Greece</title><link>https://santandermetgroup.github.io/website-demo/event/2013-assessing-fire-weather-index-using/</link><pubDate>Tue, 01 Jan 2013 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://santandermetgroup.github.io/website-demo/event/2013-assessing-fire-weather-index-using/</guid><description>&lt;p>Forest fires have always been present in the Mediterranean ecosystems, thus they constitute a major ecological&lt;br />
and socio-economic issue. The last few decades though, the number of forest fires has significantly increased, as&lt;br />
well as their severity and impact on the environment. Local fire danger projections are often required when dealing&lt;br />
with wild fire research. In the present study the application of statistical downscaling and spatial interpolation&lt;br />
methods was performed to the Canadian Fire Weather Index (FWI), in order to assess forest fire risk in Greece.&lt;br />
The FWI is used worldwide (including the Mediterranean basin) to estimate the fire danger in a generalized fuel&lt;br />
type, based solely on weather observations. The meteorological inputs to the FWI System are noon values of&lt;br />
dry-bulb temperature, air relative humidity, 10m wind speed and precipitation during the previous 24 hours.&lt;br />
The statistical downscaling methods are based on a statistical model that takes into account empirical relationships&lt;br />
between large scale variables (used as predictors) and local scale variables. In the framework&lt;br />
of the current study the statistical downscaling portal developed by the Santander Meteorology Group&lt;br />
(&lt;a href="https://www.meteo.unican.es/downscaling" title="https://www.meteo.unican.es/downscaling">https://www.meteo.unican.es/downscaling&lt;/a>) in the framework of the EU project CLIMRUN (&lt;a href="http://www.climrun.eu" title="www.climrun.eu">www.climrun.eu&lt;/a>)&lt;br />
was used to downscale non standard parameters related to forest fire risk.&lt;br />
In this study, two different approaches were adopted. Firstly, the analogue downscaling technique was directly&lt;br />
performed to the FWI index values and secondly the same downscaling technique was performed indirectly through&lt;br />
the meteorological inputs of the index. In both cases, the statistical downscaling portal was used considering the&lt;br />
ERA-Interim reanalysis as predictands due to the lack of observations at noon.&lt;br />
Additionally, a three-dimensional (3D) interpolation method of position and elevation, based on Thin Plate Splines&lt;br />
(TPS) was used, to interpolate the ERA-Interim data used to calculate the index. Results from this method were&lt;br />
compared with the statistical downscaling results obtained from the portal.&lt;br />
Finally, FWI was computed using weather observations obtained from the Hellenic National Meteorological Service,&lt;br />
mainly in the south continental part of Greece and a comparison with the previous results was performed.&lt;/p></description></item></channel></rss>