<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>Brands, S. | Santander Meteorology Group</title><link>https://santandermetgroup.github.io/website-demo/author/brands-s./</link><atom:link href="https://santandermetgroup.github.io/website-demo/author/brands-s./index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><description>Brands, S.</description><generator>Wowchemy (https://wowchemy.com)</generator><language>en-us</language><image><url>https://santandermetgroup.github.io/website-demo/media/icon_hu58a305e0ce1458c8ebaf599b64640cde_12944_512x512_fill_lanczos_center_3.png</url><title>Brands, S.</title><link>https://santandermetgroup.github.io/website-demo/author/brands-s./</link></image><item><title>A critical reassessment of statistical downscaling techniques under climate change conditions in Spain: Accuracy, distributional similarity and robustness</title><link>https://santandermetgroup.github.io/website-demo/event/2012-a-critical-reassessment-of-statistical/</link><pubDate>Thu, 01 Jan 1970 00:33:32 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://santandermetgroup.github.io/website-demo/event/2012-a-critical-reassessment-of-statistical/</guid><description>&lt;p>The performance of a wide range of statistical methods to downscale temperature (both maxima and minima) and precipitation in Spain is critically reassessed with respect to their robust applicability in climate change studies. For such purpose, we cross-validate the different techniques focusing on three distinct aspects: 1) accuracy (correlation, etc.), 2) distributional similarity (KS and PDF scores), and 3) stationarity/robustness under climate change conditions. For the latter, which is normally missed in state-of-the-art downscaling studies, we consider anomalous warm/cold (temperature) and dry/wet (precipitation) periods from the observational records - which serve as surrogates of possible future climate alterations - and test the performance of the methods, as compared to random periods. It is found that a near-perfect association between observed and downscaled series (e.g. high correlations) may hide important shortcomings in terms of distributional similarity and robustness. Therefore, a wide collection of downscaling configurations (domain-predictor-methodology) are evaluated in order to identify those being the most appropriate to deal with this issue.&lt;br />
This study is part of the work done in the project ESTCENA, a strategic action of Plan Nacional de I+D+i 2008-2011.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>A new source of seasonal predictability for the winter climate in Spain</title><link>https://santandermetgroup.github.io/website-demo/event/2012-a-new-source-of-seasonal/</link><pubDate>Thu, 01 Jan 1970 00:33:32 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://santandermetgroup.github.io/website-demo/event/2012-a-new-source-of-seasonal/</guid><description>&lt;p>In a previously published study (Cohen &amp;amp; Jones 2011), an index describing the increase of Eurasian snow cover during October (Snow Advance Index, SAI) has shown to be associated with the Arctic Oscillation (AO) in the following winter (DJF). Based on this finding, we demonstrate that a modified version of the October SAI is highly correlated with the DJF-mean North Atlantic Oscillation, as well as with the concurrent values for precipitation, insolation and wind speed over Spain. Exploiting this formerly unknown lagged teleconnection, a statistical forecasting scheme is applied to predict the above mentioned variables one month ahead. The hindcast skill obtained from a one-year out cross-validation considerably outperforms the results of any competing dynamical and empirical forecasting approach available to date.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Reference&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Brands S, Manzanas R, Gutiérrez JM, Cohen J (2012): Seasonal Predictability of Wintertime Precipitation in Europe Using the Snow Advance Index. Journal of Climate 25:4023-4028&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Cohen J, Jones J (2011) A new index for more accurate winter predictions. Geophyiscal Research Letters 38:L21701, doi:10.1029/2011GL049626&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Assessing the robustness of statistical downscaling techniques for their application under climate change conditions</title><link>https://santandermetgroup.github.io/website-demo/event/2012-assessing-the-robustness-of-statistical/</link><pubDate>Thu, 01 Jan 1970 00:33:32 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://santandermetgroup.github.io/website-demo/event/2012-assessing-the-robustness-of-statistical/</guid><description>&lt;p>In this study, the applicability of statistical downscaling (SD) methods for use in climate change studies is assessed. To this aim, we introduce a new score to estimate the robustness of these methods to warming and drying climate conditions, as given by anomalously warm/dry years in the observational record. This score is applied to assess the relative performance of twelve different methods (from the analog, weather typing, weather generator, regression and GLM families) for downscaling temperatures and precipitation in Spain. Since the temperatures in the observed warm years are significantly underestimated by the analog and weather generator approaches, special care has to be taken when applying them to GCM scenario runs. This is demonstrated by relating the robustness-score to the mean relative warming obtained from applying the SD-methods to the A1B scenario run (2071-2100) from the ECHAM5 Global Climate Model.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Actual and future trends of extreme values of temperature for the NW Iberian Peninsula</title><link>https://santandermetgroup.github.io/website-demo/event/2009-actual-and-future-trends-of/</link><pubDate>Thu, 01 Jan 1970 00:33:29 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://santandermetgroup.github.io/website-demo/event/2009-actual-and-future-trends-of/</guid><description>&lt;p>It is now very well established that yearly averaged temperatures are increasing due to anthropogenic climate change. In the area of Galicia (NW Spain) this trend has also been determined. The main objective of this work is to assess actual and future trends of different extreme indices of temperature, which are of crucial importance for many impact studies.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>As direct GCM-output significantly underestimates the variance of daily surface temperature variables in NW Spain, these are obtained by applying a statistical downscaling technique (analog method), using 850hPa temperature and mean sea level pressure as combined predictors. The predictor fields have been extracted from a multi-model multi initial conditions ensemble of 14 runs of three GCMs participating in the IPCC AR4.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>For 1960-2006 results show a significant increase of the number of days with maximum temperatures above the 90th percentile. Furthermore, a significant decrease of the days with maximum temperatures below the 10th percentile has been found. The tendencies of minimum temperatures are reverse: less nights with minimum temperatures below the 10th percentile and more with minimum temperatures above 90th percentile. Those tendencies can be observed all over the year, but are more pronounced in summer. Results for relationship between the above mentioned extreme values and different North Atlantic teleconnection patterns show that local tendencies are associated with trends of EA (Eastern Atlantic) and SCA (Scandinavian) patterns. The NAO (North Atlantic Oscillation) only in winter is related to the number of cold days.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>The ensemble climate projections generated with the analog method indicate that the observed (linear) trends of maximum and minimum temperatures in NW Spain are expected to continue in the next decades. Furthermore the uncertainty interval of these projections (2021-2050) is dominated by model uncertainties rather than by forcing uncertainties.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>We conclude that more frequent hot days as well as an increasing probability of summertime heat waves are to be expected in the next decades. Cold days tend to diminish, decreasing the probability of wintertime cold waves and leaving a greater part of the area under study without frost throughout the year.&lt;/p></description></item></channel></rss>