<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>Regional climate projections | Santander Meteorology Group</title><link>https://santandermetgroup.github.io/website-demo/tag/regional-climate-projections/</link><atom:link href="https://santandermetgroup.github.io/website-demo/tag/regional-climate-projections/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><description>Regional climate projections</description><generator>Wowchemy (https://wowchemy.com)</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Wed, 11 Mar 2015 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><image><url>https://santandermetgroup.github.io/website-demo/media/icon_hu58a305e0ce1458c8ebaf599b64640cde_12944_512x512_fill_lanczos_center_3.png</url><title>Regional climate projections</title><link>https://santandermetgroup.github.io/website-demo/tag/regional-climate-projections/</link></image><item><title>A set of regional climate change scenarios over Spain: ESCENA Project</title><link>https://santandermetgroup.github.io/website-demo/event/2015-a-set-of-regional-climate/</link><pubDate>Wed, 11 Mar 2015 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://santandermetgroup.github.io/website-demo/event/2015-a-set-of-regional-climate/</guid><description>&lt;p>ESCENA (&lt;a href="http://proyectoescena.uclm.es" target="_blank" rel="noopener">http://proyectoescena.uclm.es&lt;/a>) was part of the Spanish Strategic action on energy and
climate change. Funded by the Spanish government, this call aimed at providing the scientific basis
for the assessment of regional climate change impacts over Spain (including continental Spain, the
Balearic and Canary islands). The ESCENA project (2008-2011) agglutinated the regional climate
modelling efforts. Four different institutions contributed simulations using 4 different Regional Climate
Models (RCMs): Universidad de Castilla-La Mancha (UCLM, PROMES model), Universidad de
Murcia (UMUR, MM5 model), Universidad de Alcalá de Henares (UAHE, REMO model) and
Universidad de Cantabria (UCAN, WRF model).
The boundary forcing came from the Global Climate Model (GCM) simulations generated by the third
Coupled Model Intercomparison Project (CMIP3) for the 4th IPCC Assessment Report (AR4). We
used three different GCMs (ECHAM5-MPIOM, CNRM-CM3 and HadCM3) forced by the A1B, A2, and
B1 emissions scenarios. An interesting feature of the experimental setup in ESCENA was the
GCM/RCM matrix, which was designed to enable the comparison of different RCMs projections with a
single specific change (RCM, scenario, GCM, parameterization). This allows the exploration of the
role of different sources of uncertainty. The RCM simulations cover a common minimum domain
encompassing the whole Spanish territory with a horizontal resolution of 25 Km.
The project focused on the near future, simulating a control period (1950-2000, 1950 left as spin-up
and disregarded in the analyses) forced by the 20C3M historical scenario and continued by a 50-year
period, 2001-2050, of future projection. In this work we present the main results of the project,
focusing on the future climate projection scenarios for impact-relevant variables.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>A new high resolution climate dataset in the Basque Country: Application for ecological niche modelling and future climate impact estimates</title><link>https://santandermetgroup.github.io/website-demo/event/2013-a-new-high-resolution-climate/</link><pubDate>Wed, 18 Sep 2013 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://santandermetgroup.github.io/website-demo/event/2013-a-new-high-resolution-climate/</guid><description>&lt;p>Global bioclimatic datasets are widely used in ecological research to estimate the potential distribution of species. Although these datasets offer high resolution information, they have not been tested rigorously in smaller regions, hence, it might not be appropriate to use them for the development of species distribution models (SDMs) due to their poor representation of local climate features. Moreover, this problem may be aggravated when predicting potential distributions in the future as a consequence of the uncertainty derived from the future altered climate scenarios. Faced with this problem a high resolution grid for the Basque Country has been developed as an alternative to existing public products: The Regional Baseline Climate of the Basque Country (RCBC). In this study we have modelled tree species under different climate datasets and SDM techniques in the Basque Country (Northern Iberian Peninsula), in order to compare the RCBC with the WorldClim bioclimatic dataset (WC) in a region of complex orography.&lt;/p></description></item></channel></rss>